<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands first and second summons Two sermons preached at Paules Crosse, the one the third of Ianuarie 1612; the other the fifth of Februarie, 1615. By Thomas Sutton Batchelour of Diuinitie, then fellow of Queenes Colledge in Oxford, and now preacher at Saint Mary Oueries in Southwarke.</title>
            <author>Sutton, Thomas, 1585-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 130 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23502</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105186</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840915</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840915</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5459</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5459)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 940:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands first and second summons Two sermons preached at Paules Crosse, the one the third of Ianuarie 1612; the other the fifth of Februarie, 1615. By Thomas Sutton Batchelour of Diuinitie, then fellow of Queenes Colledge in Oxford, and now preacher at Saint Mary Oueries in Southwarke.</title>
                  <author>Sutton, Thomas, 1585-1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second impression, perused and corrected by the authour.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[10], 249, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes for Matthevv Lavv, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Fox,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The second sermon has a separate title page, with same imprint, reading: Englands second summons. A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 5. of February, Anno Domini 1615. ..</note>
                  <note>With continuous signatures and pagination.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; some print show-through and some leaves tightly bound; title page stained and torn, slightly affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5459:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5459:1"/>
                  <p>ENGLANDS Firſt and Second SVMMONS.</p>
                  <p>Two Sermons Preached at <hi>Paules Croſſe,</hi> the one the third of <hi>Ianuarie</hi> 1612; The other the fifth of <hi>Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie,</hi> 1615.</p>
                  <p>By THOMAS SVTTON Batchelour of Diuinitie, then fellow of Queenes <hi>Colledge in Oxford, and now Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher at Saint Mary Oueries in Southwarke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond Impreſſion, Peruſed and Corrected by the Authour.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>MICAH 6.2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Heare yee Mountaines the Lords quarrell, for the Lord hath a quarrell againſt his people, and hee will pleade with Iſrael.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by NICHOLAS OKES for MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THEVV LAVV, and are to bee ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the Signe of the Fox. 1616.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5459:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5459:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL MAISTER Doctour AIRAY Prouoſt of <hi>Queenes Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> all felicitie both in this world and in the world to come.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Jght Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, you may iuſtly maruell what importunity might bring my impoliſhed
<pb facs="tcp:5459:3"/>Meditations ſo quickly to the Preſſe, but (being much againſt my will enforced to let them try their fortune in the world) why I ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath them to your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection no man needs to wonder, conſidering the many encouragements, and continuall kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes which I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from you, vnto whoſe fauour, next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, I aſcribe the
<pb facs="tcp:5459:3"/>greateſt part of my wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being, ſince firſt I came vnder your gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I know well you haue many learned Scribes in that <hi>Naioth,</hi> whereof God hath made you the chiefe <hi>Seer,</hi> more worthie to haue ſhewne their forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this kinde then my ſelfe, who can leaue more learning for the gleaning, then my whole vintage. (For I am but
<pb facs="tcp:5459:4"/>one of the leaſt, and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt amongſt all the ſons of my mother) yet ſeeing you may iuſtly challenge the ſame intereſt in mee, which <hi>Paul</hi> did in <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemon, Thou oweſt vnto me thy owne ſelfe,</hi> I am willing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge ſome part of my debt, if you ſhall allow of this coine and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion for currant: and yet euen in this, ſhall J runne farther vpon
<pb facs="tcp:5459:4"/>the old ſcore, as being rather in your debt for your kinde receiuing of it, then out of your debt by repaying ſo ſlender thankes. J know that the leaſt Sabboth daies iourney of your owne, is more worth then any whole yeares paines of mine: Yet am I confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, you will both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider my yeares, which are but few, and the time J had, which
<pb facs="tcp:5459:5"/>was but ſhort, and my many other occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, wherewith in the meane time I was interrupted, and then accept of this for tryall, as if it were the extract of ſome purer and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wit. The Lord proſper your daies, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect your heart, and bleſſe all your labours, to the glorie of his Name, and the good of his Church: From
<pb facs="tcp:5459:5"/>
                     <hi>Queenes</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Yours in all duty and ſeruice,</hi> Thomas Sutton.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5459:6"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5459:6"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>ENGLANDS</hi> Summons.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>HOSEA 4.1.2.3.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Heare the word of the Lord yee children of Iſrael: for the Lord hath a controuerſie with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Land, becauſe there is no truth, nor mercy, nor knowledge of God in the Land.</p>
                        <p>By ſwearing and lying, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and ſtealing, and whoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, &amp;c.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is parcell of a Sermon, penned by <hi>Hoſea</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Beeri,</hi> contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in it a ſharpe and bitter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiue
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5459:7"/>againſt Iſrael, falling of it ſelfe into two faire and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly channels. The one an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the men of Iſrael for their crimſon ſins, from the firſt vnto the fifteenth verſe. The other a kind and gentle admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to the men of <hi>Iudah,</hi> to forbeare the dangerous paths of ſinne, wherein her ſiſter <hi>Iſrael</hi> had wearied her ſelfe, in the remnant of the Chapter.</p>
                  <p>The accuſation is laid downe in a legall and iudiciall manner of proceeding, wherein the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> are ſummoned to appeare at the bar and tribunall of Gods iudgements, there to anſwere vnto ſuch capitall offences, as there ſhould bee obiected, and laid vnto their charge: &amp; it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines in it foure ſeuerall bils of inditement, and after plaine and euident conuiction, foure ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5459:7"/>iudgements againſt them, the firſt bill is contained in the two firſt verſes, where they ſtand indited of want of truth, want of mercie, &amp;c. and the iudgement for thoſe ſins is annexed, verſe the third: <hi>Therefore the Land ſhal mourne.</hi> The ſecond bill is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the fourth verſe, where they are accuſed of two notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and inexpiable crimes; the one they would endure no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, they were impatient of wholeſome admonition; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they would not ſtick to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile the meſſengers of God, and the ſentence of the Iudge againſt this ſin is annexed, verſe the fifth: <hi>Therefore ſhall they fall in that day.</hi> The third bill is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſeuenth verſ. where ſaith <hi>Zanchius,</hi> they are accuſed of palpable and groſſe vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; for looke how faſt ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5459:8"/>the Lord heaped his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings vpon their bodies, ſo faſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues heaped a dead weight of ſinne vpon their owne ſoules; and the iudgement for this ſin is annexed in the end and clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſame verſe: <hi>Therefore will I turne their glorie into their ſhame.</hi> The fourth and laſt bill is contained in the twelfth verſe, where they are accuſed of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall whoredom; and the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for this ſin is annexed at the foureteenth verſe: <hi>Therefore I will not viſite your daughters when they are harlots, nor your ſpouſes when they are whoores:</hi> Of all which there is onely one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement, and one iudgement, comprized in the words wee haue in hand.</p>
                  <p>So that the limbes and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Text muſt needs be two. The one Gods legall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5459:8"/>with <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The other his verdict and ſtroake of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In Gods proceeding I obſerue firſt the ſummons, <hi>Heare the word of the Lord.</hi> Secondly the reaſon of the Summons; it was to debate and decide a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie.</hi> Thirdly the parties who ſtood at variance, and theſe as vnequally matched, as euer were earth and heauen, ſtrength and weakeneſſe, or the great <hi>Beemoth,</hi> and the ſillieſt worme that creepeth in the chinkes of the earth: It was God and <hi>Iſrael.</hi> God both Iudge and Plaintiffe himſelfe; <hi>Iſrael</hi> the weake and poore defendant. Fourthly the ſinnes whereof they are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and theſe are either priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue in the firſt, or poſitiue in the ſecond verſe. The priuatiue ſins are three; wherof two concerne their neighbours. The firſt, <hi>want
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5459:9"/>of Truth.</hi> The ſecond <hi>want of Mercy.</hi> The third reſpected God himſelfe, <hi>There was no knowledge in the Land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The poſitiue ſinnes are fiue; <hi>Swearing, Lying, Killing, Stealing Whooring;</hi> and euery of theſe ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauated from two circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the text. Firſt from the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garneſſe and violence of their affection in the purſuit of them: for <hi>They brake out. Perruperunt omnia repagula, quibus contineri ſolent homines à peccando;</hi> there was neither loue nor ſhame; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther awe of Gods maieſty, nor the dread of his puniſhments, that could reſtraine or keepe them backe, from gruing head and reines vnto all bloudy and crying ſins. Secondly from the vninterrupted courſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued practiſe of their ſinning, <hi>Bloud touched bloud,</hi> euery little
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5459:9"/>cottaage became <hi>Aceldema,</hi> a field of bloud. <hi>Finis vnius pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti gradus futuri,</hi> ſo ſoone as euer they had wearied themſelues with one of theſe ſinnes, they poſted with precipitant and winged haſt, without all inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of time vnto an other.</p>
                  <p>Thus ſin and ſin went hand in hand, and thus <hi>Bloud touched Bloud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The puniſhments for theſe ſinnes, which are heere liuely and emphatically diſcribed by diuers metaphors, are two. Firſt, the famine, where it is ſaid, <hi>The Land ſhall mourne;</hi> as if he ſhould thus haue ſaid: The people will not mourne for themſelues, therefore the earth (though it bee ſenſeleſſe) ſhall mourne for them; it ſhall mourne as <hi>Rahel</hi> mourned for her children, being robbed and ſtript, not onely of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5459:10"/>her fruits, but of her inhabitants alſo. The ſecond is the ſword, where it is ſaid, <hi>Euery one ſhall be cut off:</hi> and both of theſe are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aggrauated from the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality and extent of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which was to ſeize not onely vpon man who had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but alſo vpon the beaſts of the field, and the fowles of the heauen, and the fiſhes of the Sea: which laſt clauſe, that it ſhould ſeize vpon the fiſhes of the Sea, doth moſt of all exage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the wrath of God againſt them: for euen in the great and generall deluge, when man for ſinne was ſwept away with the beſome of deſolation, the fiſhes were exempted from all puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Auguſtinus de Ciuitate Dei, lib. <hi>15.</hi> cap <hi>27.</hi>
                     </note> as if they had beene a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of another world, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no commerce nor ſociety with man, were not tainted with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5459:10"/>the fluxe and leproſie of his ſinne: but now it ſeemes his wrath was hotter, in aſmuch as hee threatens to make the fiſhes alſo partakers of mans puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not that hee purpoſed to catch the ſilly fiſhes in the net of his iudgements, but onely that by theſe Rhetorical amplificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he might more feelingly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and moue the hearts of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> both with ſome touch and feeling of their owne ſins, and his puniſhments. Thus you ſee into what an Ocean of all va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety and choiſe of matter I am now ready to wade, both as faſt as God ſhall giue me aſſiſtance, and as far as the time and your Chriſtian patience will permit; and firſt of the ſummons, which was the firſt thing I obſerued in the accuſation: <hi>Heare the Word of the Lord,</hi> as if in fuller termes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5459:11"/>hee ſhould haue ſaid.</p>
                  <p>You cannot chuſe but know how carefully I haue ſollicited, how friendly I haue admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, how powerfully I haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted, how ſincerely I haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed you in matters concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God and your own peace, but my words haue periſhed in the aire, I haue ſpent my ſtrength vpon you in vaine, and for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; for how little you haue profited, how backeward you haue beene in hearkning, how ſlacke in performing, how cold in your zeale, how dead in your affection, how frozen in your obedience, theworld can teſtifie vnto your face. I haue wooed you with loue, but you neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, I haue wooed you with teares, but you neuer forrowed, I haue wooed you with promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of rewards, but you neuer
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5459:11"/>beleeued; I haue ſhaken you with menaces and threats of death and bloud, but you neuer ſuſpected that any of theſe euils ſhould come vpon you: Mercie hath ſtood and knockt at your gates, but ſhe hath beene repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; Indgement hath laid ſiege to the walles of your houſes, but you haue not beene humbled; the ſiluer trumpets of heauen, and the watchmen of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> haue rackt and ſtretched their voices, they haue filled their mouthes with ruthfull <hi>Elegies</hi> ſo paſſionate, as might haue wrung a ſtreame of teares from a heart of Iron; but you haue laughed them to ſcorne, you haue eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med their words but as an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſound, &amp; their perſons as the refuſe and vaſſals of the earth: wherefore we ceaſe from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward to ſpeake vnto you, wee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5459:12"/>will waſte no more ſtrength vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, but withall know, that the Lord will debate the matter with you himſelfe: hee ſees that his <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> cannot preuaile by Preaching mercie, therefore this dreadfull Soueraigne will come himſelfe to paſſe his iudgement; vnto which iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by vertue of a commiſſion from the Court of heauen, I warne and ſummon you, <hi>Heare word of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From whence iſſues this point of doctrine:<note place="margin">When the Preacher preuaile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s not, God beginnes himſelfe.</note> 
                     <hi>That if the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God, haue long and long contended with a people, to worke their conuerſion and cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, then will the Lord take the matter into his owne hand, and proſecute the cauſe with afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and iudgement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For proofe whereof you ſhall not need to wade farre into the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5459:12"/>Chriſtall Riuer of Gods Book. Stand but a while vpon the brink of this ſiluer ſtreaming <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loam,</hi> and you will all confeſſe with <hi>Archimedes,</hi> as if your ſelues had beene downe in the water; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, we haue found the Propoſition true, and the doctrine ſound.</p>
                  <p>When God had opened the flood gates of his loue, firſt in the admirable worke of mans creation, changing him from a little model of ſlime, into a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſubſtance: ſecondly, in the propagation of Man, increaſing his ſeed as the Stars of Heauen: thirdly, in gracing Man with do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and ſoueraignrie ouer all his creatures: fourthly, in crowning man with the higheſt perfection, and beautie of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall delights? Thus purpoſing to win his affection, and to bind
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5459:13"/>him for euer, to performe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and due allegeance vnto him; but ſtill perceiuing that theſe bleſſings made them grow rather wanton then thankefull, that they turned the dew of his graces into a rank paſture to fat themſelues in ſinne; that the oile of his mercie made them more actiue, and nimble in feates of impiety, that the ſtrength of his creatures made them more ſtrong to giue head &amp; raines to open rebellion, in the end Hee thus reſolues againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſixt of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> the third, <hi>Lo iadon ruchi.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 6.3.</note> 
                     <hi>My ſpirit ſhall no longer ſtriue with man:</hi> which Text the Rabbinshaue ſo foully mangled that it were but folly to relate their enforced expoſitions.<note place="margin">Lutherus. P. Martyr.</note> I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther embrace the iudgement of <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and then the ſenſe is pregnant for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5459:13"/>our purpoſe: <hi>My Spirit ſhall no longer ſtriue with Man;</hi> that is, I will not endure that my Word ſhould ſtill be Preached in vaine vnto them: as if in more ample forme of words hee had ſaid, they might long ſince haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of <hi>Methuſalem</hi> and of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mech,</hi> and yet they haue ſome time and reſpit to learne of my ſeruant <hi>Noah,</hi> how to poſſeſſe their ſoules in peace: but if they will not be reclaimed, then I will trouble my ſeruants no longer in woing and ſoliciting them, but after the prefixed time of an 120 yeares, I will come my ſelfe in the fierceneſſe of my wrath with an <hi>Alpheus,</hi> and invn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of water in the one hand, and a beſome of deſolation in the other, to purge this <hi>Augeum ſtabulum,</hi> which is the harbor of their ſinnes. Thus when <hi>Noah,</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:5459:14"/>whom the ſpirit of God had ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Preacher of righteouſnes, had vſed his diuineſt, and moſt powerful Rhetorique; ſomtimes as a <hi>Pericles,</hi> thundring; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as an <hi>Apollos</hi> powerfully perſwading; ſometimes like a <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> ſweetly pleaſing; ſometimes like a learned <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> ſtrongly conuincing the old world of diſloyaltie vnto God. And yet all theſe painefull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons proued but like paper bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets ſhot againſt a braſen wall; then began the Iudge of all the world to ſtir vp himſelfe like a man of warre, to muſter vp his ſergeants of death, to diſcharge whole vollies of plagues ſo thick vpon them, that ere euer hee could bee brought to ſtay his hand from ſtriking, the whole earth might haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained and mourned with <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel,</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:5459:14"/>that the greedie womb, and belly of the ſea, had ſwallowed and entombed the carcaſſes of all her children in one day, <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis</hi> 7.22.</p>
                  <p>Thus righteous <hi>Lot</hi> for many yeeres together wraſtled with <hi>Sodome,</hi> ſometime like a ſharpe Satyr whetting his ſtile with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and tart <hi>Iambicks</hi> to diſmay and grate their vnrelenting hearts: ſometimes ſweeting his diſcourſe with hymnes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, intermingling gracious promiſe of the ioyes of heauen: ſometimes ſtealing into their hearts and attentions by plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing deſcants: and ſometimes deading and appalling their wanton countenance, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the vgly viſage and frightfull portraiture of their ſin, by opening the dores and dark entries of hell, by exagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5459:15"/>the wrath and fierceneſſe of a reuenging God, by frequent and vehement ingemination of a ſpirituall <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> wherin they ſhould be chained for euer like <hi>Prometheus;</hi> of a Iudge before whom they ſhould ſtand with feare; of a indgement and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence vnder which they ſhould ſink with vtter deſpaire; of a hell and a Tophet, wherein they ſhould frie, till eternitie it ſelfe ſhold haue a period: when thus hee had vexed and wearied his righteous ſoule, and like a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lampe had waſted his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and fatneſſe with a ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and tender regard of their welfare, &amp; yet with all his labor could not pull ſo much as one ſoule out of the fire, with all his ſtrength not breake the heart of one ſin, with the ſling of <hi>Dauid</hi> not wound the head of one <hi>Goli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah:</hi>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:5459:15"/>with all the rich armorie of God, not ſo much as ſnape or coole the heate of one impiety. Then the Lord began to buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, and ioyne forces with them himſelfe, to draw a ſword like the ſword of <hi>Saul</hi> or <hi>Gideon,</hi> which neuer returned empty from the bloud of the ſlaine, and the fat of the mighty, he parlied but a while with the clouds of Heauen, and they without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murre of time vnited their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, melted and reſolued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into a ſudden and violent ſtorme, not of water, whoſe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence their ſumptuous buildings might haue abated: but of fire, which is vnreſiſtable, and that mixt with brimeſtone, which both increaſed the heate,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.24</note> and made the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t more diſtaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Thus did <hi>Moſes</hi> wraſtle and cumbat with <hi>Pharao,</hi> ſometimes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:5459:16"/>charging him in the name of God to let Iſrael go: ſometimes confounding him and his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers with miracles: ſometimes ſtriking him and his whole land with ſuch vncoth, and ſore diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as might either haue broken or bowed a heart of yron and a face of braſſe, but ſtill he harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his face like a ſtone, and would not perceiue, hee muſted his eyes like <hi>Tamar,</hi> and would not ſee, he made his conſcience like a ſmooth pauement, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heauieſt iudgement which <hi>Moſes</hi> thunderd, the ſtrangeſt miracles which hee wrought, the waightieſt plagues which the rod of the Almighty inflicted, left no marke not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; The turning of all their water into bloud, could not wring one drop of water from his eyes; the common plague
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5459:16"/>vpon all the beaſts of the Land, could not kill one ſinne in his heart, all the cold ſhowers of haile could not abate or coole his heat and rage againſt the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> of God, the Sunnes draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a black maske before her crimſon face could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him to plucke the viſard from his crimſon ſins; the killing of the firſt borne in all the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Egypt,</hi> could not kill the ſtrength of ſin in this one <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian:</hi> and therefore when the Lord ſaw that <hi>Moſes</hi> was too weake a cumbatant for ſuch a potentate, he took the cauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his owne hand, and plied him cloſe with iudgements: Firſt, daunting him with feare, and then opening the belly of the ſea, which ſwallowed him aliue. <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.20.</p>
                  <p>To this purpoſe hearken you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5459:17"/>how the Prophets complaine of <hi>Babel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 51.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 5.1.9. Wee would haue cured her, but ſhe would not be cured: come, let vs all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake her. How many paſſionate Sermons may we think that the Prophets had made? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny feruent prayers had they ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered? How often had they knockt at the dores of their hearts by powerfull exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? How ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had they knockt at the dores and windowes of heauen by ſupplications, before they would giue het ouer, or leaue her to her ſelfe to ſinke or ſwimme?<note place="margin">Zwingl. &amp; Hugo.</note> 
                     <hi>Zwinglius</hi> and <hi>Hugo Cardinalis</hi> make this place very ſtrong to back the pointin hand It is (ſay they) the appeale of all the Prophets to the court of heauen, <hi>Cil enim inter Prophet as non eſſet, qui Babylonij faſtum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primeret, eius vltio ad Dominum
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5459:17"/>delata eſt.</hi> When all the Balme in <hi>Gilead</hi> could not cure her, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they left her deplored and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate to fall into the hands of God, and when the tongues of his Prophets were wearied with crying, and their ſoules fainted and failed with labouring, and their ſpirits groned being euen tired with wooing and entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and for all this ſhee made this the burden of her ſong, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo ſanari,</hi> I will not bee healed: Then the Lord called for <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> to bee the hammer wherewith hee might breake; for the Kings of <hi>Armenia</hi> and <hi>Scythia,</hi> to bee the arrowes of his quiuer, wherewith hee might cleaue; for <hi>Cyrus</hi> and <hi>Darius</hi> to bee his gliſtring ſword, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee might gaſh and ſlice their fleſh, and to weede them man after man out of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5459:18"/>thoſe <hi>Eliſian</hi> fields, and <hi>Heſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Orchards, wherein they were planted.<note place="margin">Stephan. in apolog. pro Herodoto.</note> 
                     <hi>Stephanus</hi> in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie for <hi>Herodotus,</hi> reports of <hi>Tamberlane</hi> that warlike <hi>Scythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> that whenſoeuer he beſieged a Citie, he firſt diſplayed a white flag in token of mercy; the next day a red flag, menacing and threatning bloud; the third day a blacke flag, the meſſenger, and enſigne of death; a right parallel with the methode vſed heere by God himſelfe: His white flag, I call thoſe bands of loue, thoſe conditions of peace which God is faine to entreate at the hands of ſinners: His red flag of corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I call thoſe grating corra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiues, and aſtoniſhing iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with which the Miniſters of God ſo often vſe to break the hearts of ſuch men, as with <hi>Ionas</hi> haue ſuffered themſelues to bee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5459:18"/>ſurpriſed with a lethargie of ſin, and when Gods Heralds haue worne themſelues out of breath with long diſplaying the two flags, and cannot preuaile; then the Coronell himſelfe, whoſe Chariot is the wind, takes the blacke flag into his owne hand, hems and wals them round with feares and terrours, hee giues his ſword a charge to eate vp their fleſh, and his arrowes a charge to drinke vp their bloud, and his iron rod a charge to breake them like clay, and the ſtars a charge to fight with them as they did with <hi>Siſera,</hi> and the earth a charge to ſwallow them as it did <hi>Korah,</hi> and death a charge to mow them down like graſſe, till there ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine one man aliue to bury another.</p>
                  <p>Which one point will bee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5459:19"/>our guide to three heauenly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations; &amp; euery one of theſe a ſoueraigne remedie, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote againſt ſome ſinne. The firſt, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> a wound and terrour to the heart and conſcience of all ſuch and make a skoffe &amp; a ieſt at the threatning, which the Miniſters of God denounce againſt them for their ſins. For doth the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher tell the adulterer that hee ſhall neuer ſee the kingdome of God, &amp; will not he yet leaue off his dallying? doeth hee tell the oppreſſing Landlord, &amp; the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer that they ſhall neuer looke God in the face with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, &amp; will they not yet leaue off their grinding? doeth he tell the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable Lawyer, that the Lord is angry with him for his needeleſſe demurs, for ſuffering poore country clients to pleade ſo long at the barre, till the boxe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5459:19"/>go with all the gaines, and will he yet ſpin out the ſuite ſo long, till the client want weft to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon him? doth the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher tell the generous &amp; noble buddes of this Land,<note place="margin">M.B.</note> that your profane &amp; obſcoene ſtageplaies doe prcue the inexpiable ſtaine and diſhonour of this famous Cittie, the noyſome wormes that canker, and blaſt al hope of grace and goodnes in the bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, that they doe ſo weaken &amp; emmaſculate al the ſeeds of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe by a ſlie and bewitching inſinuation, that whereas they are planted in theſe nurceries of the Law, to be fitted &amp; enabled for the publike good, &amp; for the continnance of the glorie, and happineſſe of this Kingdome; they licentiouſly diſſolue into vngodly and wanton pleaſures, and then all hope of their euer
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5459:20"/>doing good, either vnto God, or vnto his Church, or vnto their Countrey, melteth as the Ice before the fire, and floweth away as vnprofitable waters: and will they not yet ceaſe to flocke vnto ſuch wanton Theaters, and there to ſpend their goods to no other purpoſe but to ſet their owne luſts on fire, to vphold ſchooles of lewdneſſe and of ſin, to maintaine men of a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt life, and diſſolute behauior in a calling no way warranted from God? Let all theſe caſt eye vpon the doctrine which I haue deliuered, and it will let them know, that if they refuſe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed from this trade of ſinne by the mouth of the Preacher, then the Lord will make it his owne quarrell, and whatſoeuer the Preacher hath threatned out of his booke, the Lord will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5459:20"/>it ſeuen fold into their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> this point diſcries the infinite and boudleſſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God, who often ſhewes vs his bow, but takes neither ſtring nor arrow into his hand; who will neuer begin to chide, till firſt by the mouth of the Preacher hee haue wooed vs with loue; neuer ſtrike till firſt by the mouth of the Preacher hee haue ſhaken his rod ouer our heads; neuer beginne to leauie his men of warre till firſt by the mouth of the Preacher, hee haue entreated and offered conditions of peace; neuer ſpoile before hee haue often ſpared; neuer ſmite till hee haue often cited; neuer condemne till hee haue often and often conuicted; that man might bee left without excuſe, and renew
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5459:21"/>no Plea of falſe impriſonment.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> this Doctrine is a wholeſome caueat for al the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this Land, to yeeld obedience to the Preachers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, and by repentance to conclude a preſent peace with GOD; before the Lord bee ſo highly incenſed, as to ſend out a prohibition to make his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſurceaſe from entreating, that himſelfe may ioyne iſſue in the Court, and wage the Lawe himſelfe, that where Preachers cannot preuayle by intreating, himſelfe will preuayle by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding your confuſion. You are at this day, and long haue beene, the aſtoniſhment and wonderment of all the world. God hath opened the windows of Heauen wider, and offered more grace vnto you, by the preaching of the word, then to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5459:21"/>all the Nations vnder the cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and roofe of heauen. He hath ſent his Meſſengers the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, like <hi>Noahs</hi> Doue, with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one an Oliue branch of peace in his mouth, to begge, and purchaſe a diuorce betwixt you and your ſinnes: hee hath ſent his meſſengers the Angels, with their ſwords halfe drawne, to winne your affection, and to winnow and ſift al the branne, I meane vngodlineſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe from amongeſt you. What meanes could the Lord haue vſed for your conuerſion that hee hath not already vſed? ſo that if you ſtill perſiſt in your gray and ancient ſinnes: if the Preacher thunder, and you not mooued: if the Preacher be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech, &amp; you not touched: if the Preacher threaten, and you not hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled: know this for certainty,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5459:22"/>that ere long, the ancient of daies will harrow vp your fleſh, and plow vp your skinne, and ſpend vpon you all the plagues and botches of <hi>Egypt,</hi> till you be turned like <hi>Sodome,</hi> into a fenne; like <hi>Babylon,</hi> into a Cabbin for Dragons and Oſtriches, and like <hi>Moab</hi> into a plaine: <hi>Et bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barus has ſegetes,</hi> this fruitfull <hi>Canaan</hi> and this little <hi>Naioth</hi> wherein we are planted, be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for a prey and poſſeſſion to ſtrangers. Thinke not that hee forgets you becauſe it is long before hee ſtrikes.<note place="margin">Plutar. in vita Fabiij.</note> 
                     <hi>Hannibal</hi> had no reaſon to thinke <hi>Fabius</hi> a da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, becauſe he was ſlow in marching; nor that beſieged Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in <hi>Curtius,</hi> to call <hi>Alexander</hi> a coward, becauſe hee was more readie to ſhew his clemency in ſauing them aliue, then his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood in conquering of them.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5459:22"/>And ſo from the <hi>Summons, Heare,</hi> I ſhould paſſe to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſummoned, the children of Iſrael, but that my meditations are intercepted, and I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to take view of an other Doctrine by the way as I go, offering it ſelfe vnto mee from theſe words, <hi>The Word of the Lord,</hi> and is compriſed in theſe termes.</p>
                  <p>The voice of Gods Miniſters is not the voice of man but of God,<note place="margin">The Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers voice is Gods voice.</note> backed and conuinced out of the 10. of <hi>Luke</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Hee that heareth you hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth mee;</hi> and from the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny both of Church, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 2.3. <hi>The word of God ſhall go forth of Ieruſalem;</hi> and of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thus vnto <hi>Peter: Wee are heere aſſembled to heare the things that are commanded thee of God, Actes</hi> 10.33. But moſt plainely
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5459:23"/>by the mouth of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. <hi>He receiued it not as the word of man, but as it is indeed the word of God.</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> Which point will one day bee ſure to riſe vp in iudgement, againſt all ſuch as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly deſpiſe, or but little regard the Lords Meſſage. <hi>Bone Deus in quae nos temporae reſeruaſti?</hi> In to what a miſerable time are we fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, when each crafty <hi>Achitophel</hi> ſhall haue attendance when he ſpeaketh; and euery ſillable of his diſcourſe, as if it were pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at <hi>Delphos,</hi> ſhal paſſe currant through the world for an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle? When euery hiſtrionicall <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſhall bee able to draw ſtones &amp; towers after him when he acteth? When euery proud <hi>Herod,</hi> who hath nothing in him to commend him, but his gaudy attire, ſhall yet haue all the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, and his words accounted
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5459:23"/>as the voice of God not of man? <hi>Vox illa hominem non ſonat:</hi> But for <hi>Eſay,</hi> hee may ſpeak till he be hoarſe, who will beleeue him? hee may lift vp his voyce like a trumpet, who will heare him? <hi>Dauid</hi> may play ſweetly vpon his inſtrument of ten ſtrings; and the Preacher deſcant heauenly on the ten commandements, &amp; yet who is inamored with the melodie of the one; or reformed according to the other?<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> may be rapt into the higheſt heauen, Preach nothing but ſaluation, ſlip not a phraſe which is not ſweetly enterlaced with heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eloquence, paue them the readieſt way to thoſe ioies which are vnſpeakeable; yea euen thruſt this <hi>Ariadnes</hi> threed into their hands; few or none that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard him. Thus are Gods He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raulds, eſteemed no better then
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5459:24"/>
                     <hi>Caſſandras</hi> Propheſies; his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors worſer then <hi>Iuſtinians</hi> Orators, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſuch members as the world might well want, the refuſe of men. Queſtion but a word with thoſe deſpiſers, and all the Apologie they pretend, all the rubbe they make, is the bad and corrupt life of many Preachers: this is it that makes them refuſe to heare, and puts them out of all conceit with the meſſage they deliuer. I hope I ſhall driue them from this hold, and ſatisfie their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection with a word. Know then, that when thou ſetteſt foote within the dore of Gods houſe, thy intent and purpoſe ſhould bee, to haue thy ſinnes opened, thy maladies cured, to take ſpirituall Phyſicke, for the remedie of ſome languiſhing diſeaſe which would eate vp thy
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:5459:24"/>ſoule. Wilt thou then be ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as refuſe the ſoueraigne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, becauſe thy Phyſition is ſicke of the ſame diſeaſe that thou art? Wilt not thou bee cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by this Phyſition, becauſe the Phyſition cannot cure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? What would God haue ſaid to <hi>Noah,</hi> if hee had refuſed to ſaue himſelfe in the Arke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the men that made the Arke for him, were drowned themſelues? Will not you go on the readieſt way to heauen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he that is your guide and Pilot runnes counter himſelfe? What though the water it ſelfe be not ſo cleane as thou woldſt haue it, yet it will purge and cleanſe thee? And what though ſometimes the life of the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher bee not ſo ſpotleſſe, as it might bee wiſhed? yet the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage which hee bringeth, the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5459:25"/>Word which hee Preacheth, the way which hee pointeth out, is the way of life; be his life neuer ſo wicked, his heart neuer ſo foule within him, the words which hee hath vttered will bee ſufficient to caſt and condemne thee at the laſt day.</p>
                  <p>We reade that <hi>Elijah</hi> was well contented to bee fed and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by the mouth of Rauens;<note place="margin">1. King. 17.</note> birds as rauenous and vncleane as any other; wheras God could haue fed him by the mouthes of farre cleaner birds. A good ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat for vs (ſaith <hi>Stella</hi> vpon the tenth of <hi>Luke</hi>) neuer to refuſe the food and diet of our ſoules,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Stella</hi> vpon Luke 10.</note> though the veſſels wherein it is carried, bee both vnſanctified and vncleane. The Rauens were vncleane birds, but the meate which they brought was whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome: and the caſe being all one,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5459:25"/>why ſhould a man refuſe the glad tydings of ſaluation, or ſtop his eares at the voyce of the skilfull charmer, becauſe the meſſenger that brings the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, is ouertaken with ſome knowne ſin? Or becauſe he that charmeth, ſtancheth not the iſſue of his owne corruption? I might enlarge the point both from S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aug. Cont. Donat l. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> Born. in Cant. Serm. <hi>66.</hi>
                     </note> in his 4. Book and 4 Chapter againſt the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts;</hi> and from S. <hi>Bernard</hi> in his 66. Sermon vpon the <hi>Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</hi> But I remember that I haue far to go and litle time to ſpend; wherefore I onely adde this ſhort caution and proceed. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware you murmurre not againſt the Preacher of the Word, leſt it be iuſtly ſaid to you, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to <hi>Iſrael; Non eſt murmur contra nos, ſed contra Deum:</hi> Your murmurre is not againſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5459:26"/>vs, but againſt the Lord, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.8. Deſpiſe not him that Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the Word, leaſt it be ſaid vnto you, as <hi>Paul</hi> told his <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4.8.</note> you deſpiſe not man but God. Deale not fraudulently with him that hath a charge of thy ſoule, leſt it bee ſaid vnto you as it was to <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira;</hi> you haue not dealt wickedly with man, but with God, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.4. And ſo I come to the parties here ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to the Word, <hi>The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>Iſrael</hi> (ſaith <hi>Zanchius</hi>) wee are eſpecially to vnderſtand, thoſe ten Tribes, which reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Ieroboams</hi> time, from the regiment of <hi>Iudaea,</hi> and our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſtiles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not barely <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as <hi>Iunius</hi> and <hi>Tremelius</hi> render it: but <hi>Bene Iiſrael, Iſraelis filij,</hi> ſons of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who was mightie
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5459:26"/>with God, meaning to put them in mind of their fathers vertues, that this comemoratiue might bee an argument to bring them home to their fathers foot-ſteps, and to aggrauate their ſhame, that hauing ſo religious pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, themſelues proued ſuch notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſhameleſſe Apoſtataes, from whence amongſt others, I haue made choiſe of this Note.</p>
                  <p>Good and vertuous children be loth to depart from the good example of their parents:<note place="margin">Good chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren muſt follow their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</note> So we read of <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> that hee made it his care to walke in the ſteps of <hi>Aſa</hi> his father; the firſt of <hi>Kings</hi> at the 22. Of <hi>Ezekiah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. King. 18.</note> that hee walked in the ſame ſteps that <hi>Dauid</hi> his father had done: Of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Chr. 34.</note> that hee turned nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the right hand nor to the left, but walked preciſely in the way of his father. This was a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5459:27"/>high commendation that <hi>Paul</hi> gaue the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6. And a commendation which God gaue the <hi>Rechabites,</hi> promiſing that he would crown them with a hopefull poſteritie, becauſe they followed the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly example of their father: <hi>Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ionaedab the ſon of Rechab ſhall not want a man to ſtand before mee for euer, Ier.</hi> 33. And <hi>Iſay</hi> 51.2. God thus ſpeakes to <hi>Iſrael; Conſider Abraham your father, and Sarah that bare you;</hi> they were zealous of my glorie, bee not you ſo cold. Theſe were bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſhining lampes, bee not you like blacke cloudes and emblemes of darknes. <hi>Abraham</hi> refuſed not to ſacrifice his ſon: looke on him, and refuſe not to ſacrifice thy ſinne, and vncleane affections. <hi>Saerah</hi> obeyed <hi>Abrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and called him Lord; and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5459:27"/>
                     <hi>Iſrael</hi> thou art Gods Spouſe, therefore obey thy God, &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him as Lord onely: Which vertuous imitation, not onely Chriſtians, but Heathens haue embraced.<note place="margin">Scipio Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus.</note> 
                     <hi>Scipio Africanus</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted it no ſmall diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for him to walk one foot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wry, from that courſe of life w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> 
                     <hi>Cyrus</hi> in <hi>Zenophon</hi> had gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. It was the height of <hi>Caeſars</hi> glory to walk in the ſteps of <hi>Alexander;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Caeſar.</note> Of <hi>Selymus</hi> the <hi>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> Emperor to walk in the ſteps of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> And of the <hi>Arabians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Selymus Turc. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat.</note> to imitate the life and profeſſion of their fathers: as <hi>Strabo</hi> in his ſixteenth book,<note place="margin">Strabo l. <hi>16</hi> Sabel. l. <hi>6.</hi> Exemp. c. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> and out of him <hi>Sabellicus</hi> in his ſixt book of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and firſt Chapter.</p>
                  <p>Which point ſhould bee a good encouragement for all ſorts of men, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues rich in the workes of mercy
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5459:28"/>as their fore-fathers haue done; an encouragement for Princes to follow the example of <hi>Phine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Numb. 25.</note> to be zealous for the Lords ſake. An encouragement for States and Potentates, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the example of the good Centurion,<note place="margin">Luke 7.5.</note> in ſhewing their loue vnto this Nation, and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp the Church of God. An encouragement for Ladies and Matrons, to follow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Abigail,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.</note> to encourage and relieue all ſuch as fight the Lords battell. An encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for reuerend Biſhops, to follow the example of good <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Kings 6.</note> in prouiding for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. An encouragement for Iudges, to follow the example of <hi>Othoniel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iudg. 3.9.</note> in ſauing and ſheilding the poore &amp; impotent from the yoke and ſeruitude of greater perſonages. An encouragement
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5459:28"/>for Lawyers to follow the good example of <hi>Elias,</hi> in ſtanding vp to pleade the Lords cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the fauorites of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 18. an encouragement for rich and wealthy citizens, to follow the example of <hi>Zacheus,</hi> in opening the bowels of their compaſſion to the afflicted me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.8. an encouragement for Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to follow the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah,</hi> in redreſſing their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Gods ſabboth, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.22. an encouragement for all men, of all men, of all eſtates and conditions, that if they haue fonnd and eſpied in their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, or other holy men, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent ages, any one vertue that was eminent, any one gift that was commendable, any part or qualitie that was admirable, and excellent, that they ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5459:29"/>&amp; imitate: but alas, it is now the open ſhame of our land, and a ſcar in the face of our gentrie, that they are becom ſuch as <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> taxed in the life of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> readier to imitate his foule deformities, then his valiant at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pts, or <hi>Platoes</hi> crooked ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſooner then his diuine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, or <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mering ſpeeches, ſooner then his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundnes and depth of reaſon; &amp; inſtead of imitating their ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vertues, they imitate nothing but new &amp; quaint deuices. They are full of ſtrange children, ſaid <hi>Eſay</hi> 2.6. which place if I might be bold to allegorize, or follow our Engliſh marginall, I would call their ſtrange children, their ſtrange deuices; their brainſicke imitation of the fantaſticall out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and inward corruption of all nations. Is it not a wonder to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5459:29"/>thinke that the world ſhould be come to the age of almoſt ſixe thouſand yeares, &amp; yet be ſtil in child-bed? and euery moneth in trauel of new faſhions, new ſins, new vanities, of all things new, ſaue onely of the new man, and the olde man is in ſuch requeſt with her, that the world is ready to ſay with the yong man in the Goſpell, whom Chriſt would haue had to folow him, that ſhe will indeed follow him, but firſt ſhe muſt go bury her father, ſhe hath an old man at home, that is not yet dead; an olde man, the olde <hi>Adam,</hi> the man of ſinne is yet aliue within her, till he be dead, there is no following of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>O the ſhame of this world, that men honorable and worſhipfull by deſcent, Chriſtians by profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, their fathers ioy, and their
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:5459:30"/>countries hope ſhould ſeruilely yeelde to follow the faſhions of all countries in their follies: thy attire in the beginning was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thee onely for a couer to hide thy ſhame, and therefore when thou followeſt moe faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then all other people, thou proclaimeſt it to the world that thou haſt more ſin to hide, more ſhame to couer, then al the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the world beſides. In the <hi>Italian</hi> faſhion, thou hideſt the <hi>Italians</hi> ſin: in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> thou hideſt the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> ſhame: in the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> thou hideſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſin: and in the <hi>French</hi> faſhion, thou hideſt the <hi>French-mens</hi> ſhame: for thy attire was giuen thee onely to couer thy ſhame: but I haue ſmall hope to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, the ſin is ſo ancient. I will therfore ſpare my further pains in this poynt, and proceed from
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5459:30"/>the ſummons, and arraignment to the occaſion thereof; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding of a controuerſie, which one clauſe contaynes, both the plaintife which is God, and the defendant Iſrael: what? a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie with Iſrael? the Vine which his owne right hand had planted? with Iſrael the people which he honoured? with Iſrael the ſonne whom hee adopted, and loued more tenderly then all the Nations of the earth beſides? and hath God a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie to decide with thee? then this obſeruation meetes me by the way: <hi>That no city, or people is ſo graced with priuileges,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">No nation can ſtand vnder the burden of ſinne.</note> 
                     <hi>ſo crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with bleſsings, ſo beloued of God, but ſinne will ſet GOD and them at variance, make Heauen their aduerſary, and hazzard the racing and ruinating, both of ſtate and gouernement:</hi> that common
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5459:31"/>weales, &amp; kingdoms haue a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riode, let <hi>Athens,</hi> and <hi>Sparta,</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Troy,</hi> and <hi>Niniuie,</hi> and <hi>Carthage</hi> be witneſſes, who haue at this day no other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, but paper walls to keepe their memories: but what haue been the cauſe of theſe ſubuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the moſt are ignorant. The <hi>Epicure</hi> aſcribes it vnto fortune, the <hi>Stoicke</hi> to deſtinie, <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Pythagoras</hi> and <hi>Bodin</hi> in the ſixt of his Methods vnto number,<note place="margin">Plato &amp; Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras, Bodin in <hi>6.</hi> meth Ariſt. <hi>5.</hi> Polit. <hi>12.</hi> Copernicus Cardanus.</note> 
                     <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the fifth of his Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, at the twelfth, to an <hi>aſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry</hi> and diſproportion in the members. <hi>Copernicus</hi> to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Center, of his imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie excentricke circle, <hi>Carda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> &amp; the moſt part of Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians to Stars &amp; Planets; but all theſe haue onely groped in the darkenes, &amp; being miſ-led by an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> haue ſuppoſed with
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:5459:31"/>
                     <hi>Ixion</hi> in the fable, they had fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the true <hi>Iuno.</hi> the brighteſt and the cleareſt truth, when it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued but a cloude of palpable darkeneſſe; but if wee conſult with the Oracles of God, wee ſhall find that ſinne is the onely cauſe why God falles out with his deareſt children, why hee turnes cities into aſhes, ruinates ſtates, and makes kingdoms but <hi>ludibria fortunae,</hi> euerlaſting mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of deſolation: the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are ſo pregnant in this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that the ſhalloweſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice may runne and reade abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant teſtimonies: aske of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and ſhe can witneſſe that this Doctrine is too too true, ſhee will not ſticke to tell you what ſhee was, &amp; whither ſhe is fallen, perhaps in theſe mourne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful termes, I was the Vine which GOD had planted with his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:5459:32"/>hand, and watered with the dew of heauen: I was the City of the great King, the Tabernacle of the moſt High, I could once haue ſayd with <hi>Niobe</hi> in the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, <hi>Sum foelix,</hi> I ſhall neuer haue cauſe to mourne: but heark you now how ſhe hath changed her tune, and the Epilogue of her pleaſing-ſong hath proued this doleful Elegy, I ſinned grieuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly, therefore am I in deriſion, <hi>Lamen.</hi> 1.8. I ſinned with a high hand, therefore hath he filled me with bitterneſſe, and made me drunke with Wormewood, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.15. I was ſicke from the ſole of my foot to the crown of my head, and I had not a man to ſtand in the gap to ſtop the Sword of the Almightie, therefore once was I robbed by <hi>Shiſhack</hi> King of Egypt, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 14. and now am I vtterly ſackt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5459:32"/>by the king of <hi>Babel.</hi> 2. <hi>Ki.</hi> 25. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and ſhe will tell you that ſhe was once as faire as the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> &amp; as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant as the valley of Egypt, as thou goeſt vnto <hi>Zoar;</hi> of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> &amp; ſhe will tell you, that ſhe was once the Empreſſe of all the earth, the pride &amp; beautie of <hi>Chaldea;</hi> of <hi>Iericho,</hi> and <hi>Ioſephus</hi> will tell vs in his firſt booke, <hi>De bello Iudaico,</hi> that it was a city of palme trees, whoſe beuty might haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded immortall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, but God became an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to <hi>Sodome,</hi> by reaſon of her vncleaneneſſe, and an enemy to <hi>Babylon,</hi> by reaſon of her pride, and an enemy to all the Kingdomes of <hi>Canaan,</hi> becauſe they were abetters and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of all varietie of ſinnes, ſo that they may all ſhake hands, and ſing in order this dolefull
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:5459:33"/>madrigall, <hi>Sodome</hi> may thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne, and ſay, My wantonneſſe ſet GOD and mee at variance, therefore am I burned to aſhes, and turned into a ſtinking Fen, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 19.25. and <hi>Babylon</hi> may anſwere thus, my pride ſet God and mee at variance, therefore are my pallaces made Dens for Dragons, <hi>Eſay</hi> 13.21. and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> may make vp the Conſort thus, My groſſe Idolatrie ſet God and me at variance, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath hee ſtript mee naked, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.3. Were it needefull I would tell you of the Churches of <hi>Corinth, Galatia, Philippi, Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Smyrna, Nice, Laodicea, Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia, Conſtantinople,</hi> of all the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne and <hi>African</hi> Churches, once like ſo many watered Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, moiſtned with all the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhowers &amp; dew of Heauen, while other places of the world
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:5459:33"/>remained, like the mountains of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> wheron there fel neither dew nor raine, they were watred like the fleece of <hi>Gideon,</hi> while the earth was dry round about them, but ſince they haue ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aſide, like the men of <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im,</hi> they haue beene ſetled vpon the <hi>Lees</hi> with <hi>Moah,</hi> they haue plowed <hi>Aceldama,</hi> a field of bloud, and ſowen iniquitie; therefore had the Lord a long fuite &amp; controuerſie with them, but in the end wiped out their names, diſcarded their Idoles, gaue their Land to be inhabited by <hi>Zijm</hi> and <hi>Ochim</hi> Turkes and Infidels.</p>
                  <p>And if euer, then would God, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> that at this time, and in this poynt, my voice were like the voice of ſom thundring <hi>Pericles,</hi> and my Pen yron, and my ſides braſſe, &amp; my ſpeech powerfull,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:5459:34"/>and my praiers effectual to rent, and moue the hearts of thoſe, who by their outragious ſinnes make God fall out with vs, and egerly importune the Iudge of all the World to denounce a doome of death and deſolation vpon this Land; as hee hath done vpon thoſe Cities which we mentioned. The world can tell, that of all the Trees in the Garden, we are the Vine, amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt all the varieties of flowers, we are the Lillies &amp; the Roſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all cities wee haue <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem;</hi> amongſt all the Princes we onely had a <hi>Deborah,</hi> and we haue a <hi>Dauid;</hi> amongeſt all the Prophets of the Lord, we haue the moſt reuerend <hi>Eliſhaes;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt all the nurceries and ſprings of learning, we haue the moſt famous <hi>Naioths,</hi> wee are they, vpon whoſe heads the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taractes</hi>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:5459:34"/>of Heauen haue beene opened, that wee might fill our ſelues with that Manna which might long ſince haue wiped out the blacke ſpots and ſtaines of ſinne, which are the caracters of Hell: theſe are our high and rich prerogatiues, wherein we may out-vie the felicitie and pride of forraine Nations. But will this Summers gleane of our proſperitie neuer bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowed? Will our Sunne neuer ſtoope below the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon? yet (beloued) we harbour ſuch armies and bands of ſins, wee are in league and compact with ſuch prodigious vices; wee take part with Mammon againſt God, when wee wedde our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections to the World like <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas;</hi> wee take part with <hi>Baal</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, when we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to wink at our Recuſants,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:5459:35"/>and the Calues which are ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethel;</hi> we take part with the fleſh againſt God, when wee do yeelde our bodies which ſhould be temples of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, to bee defiled with filthy ſtrumpets; we take part with all the powers of darkneſſe againſt GOD, and our owne ſoules, when wee are content to ſpend our goodes, beſtow our time, waſte &amp; conſume our bodies, in rearing a <hi>Babell</hi> with the one hand, wherein we ſhal ſport our ſelues a while, though with the other we be digging vp a hell &amp; a Tophet, wherein without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, we fry for euer: thus haue wee flowne in the face of the bleſſed Trinitie, who neuer did vs wrong; wee haue dared our God to his face; our whole Land beginnes to ſwarme with ſinnes, as thicke as Egypt did
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:5459:35"/>with frogges; wee are already growne ſo farre, and yet we are going ſo faſt, that a man would thinke, that many of vs did at this day contend &amp; ſtriue, who ſhould out-ſtrippe another, and be formoſt in hell.</p>
                  <p>What then can we expect, but that God whom wee haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraind to be our enemy, ſhould beginne to make furrows in our backes, to ſtrike our heads with giddineſſe, our faces with pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; to call againe for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible Armado, like to that of 88. for a new powder-plot of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian Doegs,</hi> that our Land may be a prey to thoſe that ſeeke our liues; ſuffer our Churches to be turned into Mannors, and the houſes of the Prophets be layd on ruinous heapes: this and no other, will bee the deciſion and finall determination, of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:5459:36"/>that controuerſie between God &amp; this Land, vnleſſe by a floud of teares wee can ſtop the way; vnleſſe by ſpeedie repentance wee can dull the edge of his ſword that is ready drawne, and ſlacke the ſtrings of his bowe, that is alreadie bent for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: the moſt ſecret plots &amp; treaſonable conſpiracies, that are wrought againſt vs, are not halfe ſo dangerous, the nefari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous proiects of all the Ieſuites in the world, (thogh their heads be the richeſt ſhops the Diuell hath, for deuiſing of bloudy at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts) are not halfe ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, all the Stratagems, the gunne-ſhotte and the powder that Hell can helpe them vnto, are not ſo forcible, nor ſo likely to interrupt the peace and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of our State and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as our ovvne ſinnes
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:5459:36"/>are, theſe onely (our ſinnes I meane) are the enemies that are moſt like to ring our knels and proclaime our Funerals: Theſe onely (our ſins I meane) are the <hi>Edomites</hi> which are moſt like to make a ſhort cut in our peace, to ſet a ſudden ſtop and period to our proſperity, to make a cracke in our hope, to alter the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aſpect of the heauens, to ſtint the influence of Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious fauour, to procure our woe, and to giue our whole State, our whole Kingdome, a blow that can neuer be healed. Giue mee leaue therefore for cloſure of the point, to exhort you (Right Honorable) and all the reſt, in the name of God, now at laſt to bethinke your ſelues of ſome remedy: God hath put a ſword of authority in your hand, for no other purpoſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:5459:37"/>but to ſtrike at ſinne; if yet you ſuffer it to ruſt in the ſheath (I am not afraid to tell you) that either you are afraid to quarrell with ſinne, or elſe you be are it ſome good will your ſelfe; or elſe you haue but malt hearts, and white liuers, and cold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, ready to faint and ſhrinke in the Lords cauſe: and ſo by your meanes ſinne ſhall haue a continuall Spring, no Autumn, not one leafe of it fall, but our Land ſhall feele a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Autumne and falling from its ancient glory, but ſee no Spring; and a continuall Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vexed with the ſtormes and ſhewers of heauens diſpleaſure, but neuer ſee nor feele the warmeneſſe of Summer. Strike then at the root of ſin, for ſin ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth at the root, and ſhaketh the foundation of our Land: But if
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:5459:37"/>our reuerend Iudges ſuffer him that ſitteth vpon the Bench, to wrong him that ſtandeth below the Barr waiting for iuſtice; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let him know that he maintaines a ſin, and then we all know that he doth his beſt to ruinate our Land. If the Gentry grow rich and potent by turning Tenants out of dores, by depopulation, by clipping or ſelling the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites portion, then let them know that they maintaine a ſin, and then wee all know they doe their beſt to ruinate this Land: If Merchants and men of Trade grow rich and powerfull by fraud and cheating, theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be vnderminers of our State, they do their beſt to ruinate this Land. Good Lord what will become of vs, when foule ſinnes in this Citie become rich profeſſions, and yet they are the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:5459:38"/>Mothes that are eating, they are the Cankers that are fretting, they are the Vermine that are vndermining both our Church and Kingdome. The ſumme of all is this, if wee continue in our ancient courſe and trade of ſin, it is as ſure as if God had ſealed it, we ſhall be either made a prey vnto our enemies, or haue our fleſh ſo full of Gods poyſoned arrowes, that it were better for vs to die then to liue: Let it then bee our ioint and greateſt care, to empty our houſes, to cleanſe our ſtreets, to weede the cockle and darnell out of this Land, that God may bee pleaſed long and long, to continue his true Religion, our peereleſſe King, &amp; this little Kingdome, in peace and happineſſe. Remember what I ſay, and I ſay it againe: Let it be your care (Right Honorable)
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:5459:38"/>to ſtrike at the roote of ſinne in the Citie: Let our reuerend Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſtrike at the roote of ſin in the Courts, on their Benches, in their Circuites: Let my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the Miniſterie, ſtrike at the root of ſin in their charges: Let euery man that cares for <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that loues our Nation, that fauours Religion, that wiſheth the glorie of our Lord to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, that hath a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> and a Chriſtian heart, fling one ſtone at the face, make one wound in the fore-head of ſin; and I beſeech God that the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens may giue you good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and that the Lord may be with you, all you valiant men: And ſo I ſhould come ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to the particular crimes whereof <hi>Iſrael</hi> is accuſed.</p>
                  <p>All which ſinnes are reduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to two heads: ſome are pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiue
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:5459:39"/>in the firſt, <hi>viz. Want of Mercy, &amp;c.</hi> ſome poſitiue in the ſecond verſe, <hi>viz Swearing, &amp;c.</hi> But before I aduenture this maine Ocean obſerue by the way;<note place="margin">Neglect of duties en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned is no ſmall ſinne.</note> That the neglect of a duty commanded, diſpleaſeth God as well as the committing of ſins prohibited; ſeeing this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie betwixt God and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> aroſe not onely from the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſins, wherein they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted things forbidden, but from the priuatiue alſo, wherein they were careleſſe of duties enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. God curſed <hi>Meroz,</hi> not for fighting againſt the people of God, but becauſe they did not aſſiſt them againſt the mighty, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.23. <hi>Diues</hi> fryed in hell, not for robbing, but for not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing <hi>Lazarus, Luke</hi> 16. The vnprofitable ſeruant was caſt <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, into vtter darknes,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:5459:39"/>not for ſpending, but for not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing his Maiſters talent. The ſiue fooliſh Virgins were ſhut out of dores, not for abuſe in waſting, but for wanting of Oile. And the wicked ſhall bee condemned at the laſt day, not for reauing the meate from the hungry, but for not feeding them; not onely for diſlodging the ſtranger, but for not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining him; not onely for ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the naked out of his clothes, but for not clothing him, not onely for wronging the ſick &amp; comfortleſſe, but for not viſiting, and for not comforting of him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. Vice &amp; Vertue are contraries which want a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium,</hi> &amp; therfore the abſence of the one in <hi>ſubiect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> capaci,</hi> argues the preſence of the other; ſo that if we be deſtitute of vertue, then are wee attended with troopes
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:5459:40"/>of vices. If our houſes be cleane ſwept and empty of ſpirituall graces, then they are conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent lodgings for vncleane ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: If wee bee not graced with knowledge, then are we mufled and blinded with ignorance: If voide of faith, wee are clothed with infidelity; If once wee giue ouer doing good, then we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute our ſelues to all ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And therefore the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of a dutie which is enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, being alwaies accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſome bolts and ſcarres of fouler ſins, is ſufficient mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter both of enditement and of iudgement, whenſoeuer the Lord ſhall ſummon vs to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before him.</p>
                  <p>A ſpeciall caueat for vs, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> not with ſimple Ideots to bleſſe our ſelues, becauſe we are harmleſſe and doe no man wrong; or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:5459:40"/>wee are not tainted with the continuall fluxe or bloudy iſſue of ſuch ſins as would make vs odious in the world; or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee breake not with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, into the outward act of ſuch ſins as are monſtrous, and deſerue the ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſure of the Law. For God hath not onely forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the euill, but commanded the good: What if thou ſteale not from thy brother, yet if thou open not thy hand to ſuccour him, thou art a robber? What if thou doſt neither lienor ſweare, yet if thou make not thy mouth a glorious Organ, &amp; thy tongue a golden Trumpet, to Preach and proclaime his loue and mercy, thou art a deepe and a round offender? What if no man can condemne thee for any euill, yet vnleſſe God and thy own conſcience ſhall commend
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:5459:41"/>thee for ſome good thou haſte wrought, I tremble to tell thee how far thou art from the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. The Iudge may not bleſſe himſelfe in this, that hee neuer hindred the poore, for if he haue not furthered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; nor in this, that hee neuer kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſuites and contentions, for if hee haue not laboured to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and ſmother them, hee hath but a diſloyall heart, &amp; the Lord will one day bee quit with him for it. The Land-Lord may not bleſſe himſelfe in this, that hee neuer wrung nor gript the bowels of his tenants, for if hee haue not ſuccoured and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted them; Nor in this, that hee neuer wronged the Church, for if he haue notpropt &amp; ſtreng the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, his zeale hath beene but cold, the Lord will one day bee quits with him for that. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:5459:41"/>that hath the charge (I will not ſay the cure of ſoules, ſeeing many haue the charge, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue care of diſcharging their duties) may not bleſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in this, that he neuer ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his people out of the way, for if he haue not painefully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed them in the right way; nor in this, that he neuer did the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrong, for if hee haue not wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ouer them to do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good, their bloud ſhall bee required at his hand, and the Lord will bee quits with him for that. Let it be the ſhame of thoſe that ſit in darknes, and are proud of their ignorance, to ſay they haue as good ſoules, &amp; hope to be ſaued aswel as any, becauſe they do no man any harme; but for vs who may ſit all day long at the feet of ſome good <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> and euery houre of the day may heare ſome
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:5459:42"/>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> Preaching vnto vs; not onely renounce the euill, but do the good; not onely ceaſe to do euill, but learne to do well; not onely abiure carnall and ſenſuall delights, the huskes and maſt whereon the worldling is like to ſurfet, but alſo make a couenant with our eyes, that they ſport themſelues with looking onely vpon the beauty of heauen; with our affections, to wed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues onely to the ioyes of heauen. Be couetous, I would haue thee ſo, ſo that thou couet no trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure but ſpirituall: Be ambitious, I would haue thee ſo, ſo thou affect no honor but immortall; Renounce all kinde of peace, wherein thou findeſt no peace of conſcience; Diſcard all ioyes, wherein thou feeleſt not the ioy of the Holy Ghoſt: <hi>Hoc fac &amp; vines,</hi> doe this and thou ſhalt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:5459:42"/>liue in the feare, thou ſhalt die in the fauour, thou ſhalt reſt in the peace, thou ſhalt riſe in the power of God the Father, and helpe to make vp the conſort in ſinging of <hi>Halleluiah, Halleluiah, all glory, and honour, and praiſe, and immortalitie, be aſcribed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lambe, and to him that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vpon the Throne for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> And now I am come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further defrauding of your expectation, to the particular grieuances whereof God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines; and the firſt of thoſe is <hi>Want of Truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Hebrew word <hi>Emeth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Zanchius,</hi> ſignifieth that kinde of fidelity, which <hi>Tully</hi> called, <hi>Dictorum conuentorum conſtantiam,</hi> and this truth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times reſpects the heart, and is called ſimplicity and integrity, ſometime the outward carriage
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:5459:43"/>in word or ſpeech, and is called truth; ſometimes the works and actions, and then is called iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and vpright dealing: ſo that when the Lord chargeth them with want of Truth, his meaning is, there was no inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie, or ſimplicitie, in their hearts, therefore there was hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; no verity in their ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, therefore lying; no iuſtice in their actions, therefore frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent and deceitfull dealing. I will wrappe vp all in this one concluſion.</p>
                  <p>All diſſimulation in the heart,<note place="margin">Firſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular grieuance.</note> and lying in the tongue, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in the outward action, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt man and man, makes God and man at oddes and variance. The, firſt which is diſſimulation in the heart, proued from the example of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira,</hi> why didſt thou conceiue
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:5459:43"/>this in thy heart? <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Actes</hi> 5.4. The ſecond which is lying in the tongue, excludes from heauen, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22. The laſt, which is deceit in the outward action, is condemned, <hi>Leu.</hi> 19. Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in the heart is the badge &amp; cogniſance of ſuch deplored wights as ſhall neuer ſee the face of God with comfort, <hi>Iob.</hi> 13.16. Lying in the tongue is the badge and cogniſance of the children of the deuils getting, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.44. Deceit in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward action is the badge and cogniſance of him that deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his God: nay, of him that ſhall beare the wrath and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God, 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.8. It is moſt true which <hi>Syracides</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, <hi>Animaquae diſſimulat, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celerat miſeria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the ſoule that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth increaſeth his paine, <hi>Eccleſiaſtic.</hi> 2. and true which <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:5459:44"/>obſerued out of <hi>Wiſedome Os quod mentitur perdit animam'</hi> the tongue that lieth,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 1.11.</note> murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſoule, and true which <hi>Moſes</hi> obſerued, <hi>Manus iniuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the hand that dealeth falſely is abhomination, <hi>Deu.</hi> 25. This is Gods inditement which you haue heard; wilt pleaſe you to heare the verdict which the Iury of the Prophets brings in againſt them?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> and <hi>Ieremy,</hi> as fore-men in the name of all the reſt, haue penned it thus: <hi>Euery one of them is an hypocrite and a diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler, Iſaiah</hi> 9.16. And <hi>Ieremy</hi> thus: <hi>They haue no courage for the truth: Ieremy</hi> 9.3. This is the verdict which the Grand-Iury of greater Prophets haue brought againſt them; and the verdict of the Petty-Iury, I meane the leſſer Prophets, is the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:5459:44"/>very ſame, regiſtred by <hi>Michah,</hi> as prolocutor for the reſt, <hi>There is none righteous amongſt them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man hunteth his brother with a net, Micah.</hi> 7.2. Thus the Iurie hath found them guilty: wil you now heare how the Lawe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes, when the Iudge paſſed this ſentence, <hi>Lying lips are abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lord, Prou.</hi> 12.22. He ſhews he had a whip prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for liars, when hee plagued <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira, Acts</hi> 5. hee ſhewed his loue to all diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers, when he diſmiſſed all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull dealers out of his houſe, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 101. He ſhewed he had a whip laid vp for all deceiuers, &amp; the lighteſt of theſe is a doome too heauy for them to beare.</p>
                  <p>See then the eminent and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant danger whereunto men of all eſtates wreſt themſelues, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> by renouncing and diuorcing of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:5459:45"/>truth, they make a breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them &amp; God that can not be cloſed, they ſow ſuch ſeed of debate and contention betwixt them &amp; God, as cannot be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered; they challenge ſuch a dreadfull war betwixt them and God as will neuer be ended, till the ſword of the Almighty hath wearied it ſelfe, &amp; the arrows of God haue made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k, and death the Axe of God haue ſurfeted it ſelfe with blood: and yet, were there a priuy ſearch to go through each <hi>Maeander</hi> and corner of the earth to ſeeke for truth; it would be as hard to find, as honeſty was in <hi>Athens,</hi> when <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſought it with a candle at noone-tide, or goodneſſe in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> when there was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prieſt nor People that exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted iudgement, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Terras Aſtraea reliquit,</hi> truth hath taken
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:5459:45"/>her ſelf vnto her wings, ſhe hath hid her ſelf &amp; will not be found. ſend priuie Search to all the ſhops of Merchants and men of Trade, and when you haue done your beſt, you may write this vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the doores; <hi>Has aedes Aſtraea reliquit,</hi> Had truth beene one of our apprentices, we ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner haue ſold our wares ſo deare if wee had more truths in our mouthes, we ſhould haue leſſe mony in our coffers: ſend priuy Search into our courts of Law, and when you haue done, you may write this vpon the Barre, <hi>Has ſedes Aſtraea reliquit,</hi> trueth hath abated too much of our fees: we ſhould haue beene but beggers if we had not baniſht it: ſend priuie Search amongſt our Stateſ-men, and when you haue done, you may write this vpon their gates for the world to read
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:5459:46"/>
                     <hi>Aſtraea &amp; domes &amp; domines reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit,</hi> in this houſe truth reſignes to policie, diſſimulation is the ready way to rich preferment: ſend priuy Search to ſeeke for truth in the very Pulpit, which ſhould be the Arke of Truth &amp; Cuſtoder of Gods ſacred Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue done, you may ſet this on many Churches and Pulpit dores, <hi>Veritas exulat,</hi> truth is brought vnder hatches, either ſhe is aſhamed, or els ſhe dares not ſhew her head; whiles ſome for raking a litle profite, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for feare of mens diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſowe pillows vnder the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes of great perſonages, and ſuffer lowd ſinnes to eſcape like the adultereſſe in the Goſpell: becauſe they are graced with greatnes and authority. Seeing then our Tradeſ-men ſell trueth for coine, our Lawyers for fees,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:5459:46"/>and our Stateſ-men for prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; our Clergy to pleaſe a Patron, how can we thinke the Lord will not come to viſite vs for theſe things, &amp; his ſoule be auenged on ſuch a Nation as this? what then remains but that we either cal truth home, which we haue baniſhed by the law of <hi>Oſtraciſme,</hi> that it may be an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice to our Merchants and men of trade, a Counſeller, and Sergeant at the Law, a Retainer &amp; Penſioner to our me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſtate, and Vſher to all the Clergie of the Land, or elſe looke euerie day for Gods arreſt vpon vs; the heauens wil not ſtil repriue their iudgements, the Sergeants of GODS wrath will not alwayes ſleepe, all the vials which God holdeth in his hand, are not full of balme &amp; oile to heale &amp; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; ſome of them are running
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:5459:47"/>ouer with gall and addle, ſome ready to vent the lees, &amp; ſowreſt dregs of Gods diſpleaſure vpon this Land, <hi>Quae ſemper imitatur eorum facta quorum exitum et ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itium perhorreſcit,</hi> which ſhrinks and trembles at <hi>Iſraels</hi> fearefull ſentence; but makes neyther ſtop nor rubbe at <hi>Iſraels</hi> crying ſins which wrings her hands, &amp; knockes her breaſt ſo often, as ſhee either heares or reades the diſmall Sentence which God pronounced againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but will neyther weepe nor cry, nor ſhed a teare for her ſelf, althogh ſhe lie rotting in the ſame cage of vncleanneſſe, and foming in the ſame menſtruous blood which made <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſo loathſome vnto God. Let it therefore bee the care of our Magiſtrates to fetch home &amp; encourage truth; of our Iudges to defend &amp; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:5459:47"/>the truth; of the Clergie to preach and ſpeake the truth; of our godly and religious Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens to lodge and harbor truth: let vs ſhew our ſelues to be true <hi>Nathanaels,</hi> in whom there is no guile, &amp; put in practiſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets rule, <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.16. Speake ye euery man the trueth vnto his neighbour, and loue not deceit, for that is the thing that the Lord hateth. And ſo I proceed to the ſecond particular grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance whereof <hi>Iſrael</hi> is indited in the next word, <hi>Ve en cheſed, No mercie;</hi> which word <hi>cheſed</hi> comprehends in it all workes of Charitie and Chriſtianitie, but I cannot inſiſt vpon explication, the point is this.</p>
                  <p>Want of mercie is a ſinne that crieth loude,<note place="margin">Second parti cular grieuance</note> and knocketh hard at heauen for vengeance, I ſhall not neede prodigally to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:5459:48"/>ſpend either breath, or time in ſtrengthning or ſupporting this clauſe of truth. S. <hi>Iames</hi> hath put the matter out of difference, <hi>Ia.</hi> 2.13. There ſhall be iudgement merciles to him that ſhewes no mercy; it was want of mercy that called for a weltering Ocean to ſwallow the hoſte of <hi>Pharao, Ex.</hi> 15. It was want of mercie that cauſed <hi>Gideon</hi> to harrow &amp; ſlice the fleſh of the men of <hi>Succoth</hi> with thorns and briars, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 8.7. it was want of mercy that hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all <hi>Nabals</hi> poſterity, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. It was want of mercie that opened the bellie and boſome of hell, to deuoure and intombe the ſoule of <hi>Diues, Luke</hi> 16. It was want of mercie (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi>) that brought the men of <hi>Delphos</hi> ſo lowe on their knees,<note place="margin">Plutar. de ſera numi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis vind.</note> that they were enforcod to proclaime it by the mouth of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:5459:48"/>criers, thorow all the markets &amp; aſſemblies of <hi>Greece,</hi> that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer would, ſhould come and be auenged on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the death of <hi>Aeſope.</hi> It was want of mercy (ſaith <hi>Beatus Rhenanus</hi>) that made <hi>Hatto</hi> that infamous clark and Biſhop of <hi>Moguntia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Beatus Rhenanus.</note> to bee chaſed to death by an Armie of Rattes. It was want of mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the little ſop and handfull of ſeed, which God had planted in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> that made all the land of <hi>Egipt</hi> to rocke, and the pillars therof to grow like the cracking of a decayed veſſell, being ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waued by the vndanted rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſome violent and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth ſtormes; all of theſe ium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping with that of <hi>Syracides, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 35.18. <hi>The Lord will not be ſlacke, the Almighty will not tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, till he haue ſmitten in ſunder the loynes of the vnmercifull.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:5459:49"/>
                  <p> And haue not we deſerued to drinke our bellies full of theſe waters of <hi>Marah</hi> as wel as they? may not we tune all our Songs vpon this note, <hi>Help Lord?</hi> &amp; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, <hi>There is no mercie?</hi> our hands are dried &amp; withered, <hi>help Lord:</hi> merciful men are gone out of the world, <hi>Eſay</hi> 57. Our Land begins to ring, &amp; our eares are filled with ſuch ruthfull and ſad complaints as theſe, <hi>Helpe Lord, there is no mercie.</hi> Our Church bemones her ſelfe thus, <hi>Helpe Lord, there is no mercie.</hi> And is not hir complaint as iuſt as any, when ſo many hungry ſouls like poore <hi>Lazarus,</hi> would gladly gather vp the crums of a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, from the mouth of their Paſtor, but cannot haue it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo many zealous chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the land, would ſit all the day long at the feet of ſome <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliel,</hi>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:5459:49"/>&amp; gladly ſtep into <hi>Betheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da;</hi> but either their Angell is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> home, or elſe hee is not able to trouble the water for them. Our Commons doe bemone them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues thus, <hi>Help Lord there is no mercie:</hi> And is not their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint as iuſt, when Land-lords are become tyrants, &amp; Tenants be made but ſlaues to ſerue their turne? and <hi>Naioth</hi> in <hi>Ramah</hi> (I meane the Nurceries of Artes and Sciences) bemones her ſelfe thus, <hi>Help Lord, there is no mercy:</hi> And is not her complaint as iuſt as any, when ſo many gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den wits, likely to haue proued the gracious ornaments and pride of their mother; are daily enforced to trie their fortune ſome other way, being vtterly diſcoraged for want of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? and our courts of Iuſtice bemone themſelues thus, <hi>Helpe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:5459:50"/>Lord, there is no mercy:</hi> and is not their complaint as iuſt as any? when the Lawyer, who ſhould be an <hi>Atropos</hi> to cut the threed, feedes his Client with golden hopes and ſugred wordes, and proues a <hi>Clotho</hi> to ſpin, &amp; a <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſis</hi> to drawe in length the threeds of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention: what chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hart would not indite both bitter &amp; tart <hi>Iambicks?</hi> or whoſe bowels wold not yerne &amp; groan within him? to ſee how the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſer of this worſt Age, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployes and ſets his beſt wits on tenters, to ioine houſe to houſe, land to land, and field to field, till there be not left a Cottage nor a Corner for the poore to dwell in; not a Common nor Paſture for them to feed in, and if it were poſſible, ſcarce whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ayre enough for them to breathe in. Whoſe heart would
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:5459:50"/>not boile &amp; melt within him, to ſee how the worlds Alchymiſt wraſtles &amp; ſtriues to turne eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry corner of his field into a beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull garden? euery litle garden into a glorious paradiſe? euerie litle cottage into a pallace? their clothes &amp; garments into robes? their tables into ſhrines? their cheſts and coffers into rich mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals of gold and ſiluer? and all this by turning good houſe-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers into beggers, and tenants out of dores. Whoſe bowels wil not roll within him, to ſee how great men take away the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s bread, wheron both church &amp; common wealth ſhould feed, &amp; caſt it vnto whelps, that they may be nouriſhed? vnto kites &amp; hawkes, that they may be ſtufft and gorged in their mews while Chriſt Ieſus in his diſtreſſed members, hath his face withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:5459:51"/>with hunger, &amp; his feet par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with colde, and his ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke grated, nay girt, &amp; paſted vnto his ſides, for want of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, for want of ſuſtenance? Whoſe heart would not bleed to ſee many houſes,<note place="margin">Ouid Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Tecta ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mibus alta columnis;</hi> goodly and tall as <hi>Babel,</hi> but not an almes at their dores, ſcarce ſmoke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them? to ſee ſuch ſpatious barnes, ſo litle kindeneſſe? to ſee how that in ſwallowing the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of God, euery one of vs is like the monſter <hi>Briareus?</hi> wee haue an hundred hands to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, but in relieuing and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the want of other, wee haue but one hand, &amp; that dried and withered, like the hand of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 13. How then can we thinke that the Lord will not viſit vs for theſe things, and his ſoule be auenged on ſuch a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:5459:51"/>nation as this? They that ſhould be a ſtaffe vnto the feeble, are of all others the readieſt to bring them vpon their knees: they that ſhould be eies to the blinde, are the fouleſt moates &amp; beames, to put out rhe eies of them that ſee: they that are ordained to chear the faces of the poore, are the onelie men to grinde and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe them: they that ſhould ſtand in the gap, like <hi>Moſes,</hi> to ſaue them from all annoyance, are of all others the moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to feed them with worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood &amp; the water of affliction, as <hi>Ahab</hi> did <hi>Micaiah</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, 1. <hi>Ki.</hi> 22. And ſhall not the Lord be auenged on ſuch a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as this? wherefore (beloued) let me try if I can perſwade you in the words of S. <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bern de modo bene viuendi.</note> 
                     <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae tuae gratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feceris ſi miſericors fueris,</hi> thou ſhalt do well to thy
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:5459:52"/>ſoule by ſhewing mercy: in the words of S. <hi>Ambroſe:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ambroſ. <hi>1.</hi> Tim. p. <hi>8.</hi> Tract. <hi>5.</hi> in Iohan.</note> 
                     <hi>Nil ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dat animu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſtianum,</hi> Nothing that God reſpects ſo much as mercy: in the words of S. <hi>Auguſtine: Charitas tua viſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra percutiat:</hi> Be yee rich in the workes of mercie. <hi>Prouocaris Chriſtiane, prouocaris à viduâ in certamen:</hi> the poore Widdow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> muſt tutor thee to be merciful; <hi>Iob</hi> muſt reade thee a Lecture of mercie, who had beene both eye vnto the blinde, and feete vnto the lame, and a father to the poore, <hi>Iob</hi> 29. Let me beſeech you in the words of the Prophet, <hi>Zacharie</hi> 7.9. <hi>Shew mercy euery man vnto his brother:</hi> let me beſeech you in the words of <hi>Peter,</hi> 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 3. <hi>Loue as bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and be mercifull:</hi> In the words of <hi>Paul, Coloſſ.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Now therfore as the elect of God holy &amp;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:5459:52"/>beloued,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>put on the bowels of compaſſion;</hi> let your mouthes bee filled with talking, your hearts with contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, your hands with working the workes of mercy while you liue, that when your life ſhall be runne out of breathe, you may heare the ſentence of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Bleſſed are the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, for the Lord hath plenty of mercy in ſtore for them.</hi> And ſo I come to the third particular grieuance: <hi>No knowledge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In which words (ſaith <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi>) wee are to note; firſt,<note place="margin">Third par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular grieuance. <hi>Crimen &amp; exaggeratio criminis.</hi>
                     </note> the crime; ſecondly, the aggrauati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The crime, they were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they had no knowledge: Which is as much as if hee thus had ſaid; you are ſo farre from ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing mee, that you know not whether I am your God or no. What do I telling you of want
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:5459:53"/>of truth or want of mercy? ſins of the ſecond Table, not ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately againſt my honour. There is a worſe fault in you then both theſe, there is a ſinne againſt the firſt Table, which doth more neerely impeach my Maieſtie, and that the very root and ſtemme of all ſin, of all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, <hi>You haue no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:</hi> the aggrauation is from the generality and proceeding of the ſins, he ſaith not there was no knowledge of God in you, but in <hi>totâ terrâ,</hi> in the whole land. It was a vniuerſal contagio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that infected all the ten tribes: much might hence be gathered, but me thinkes the point that is moſt obſerueable ſhold be this.</p>
                  <p>Ignorance,<note place="margin">Ignorance the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſin.</note> in things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God, is the mother and root of moſt fearefull and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſins, and therfore it is that
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:5459:53"/>all ſinnes be called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and beare the name of ignorance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.7. Ignorance was the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural mother that brought <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſo many ſinnes into the world; or elſe God himſelfe ſhot ſhort of truth, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 95. <hi>My people erre in their hearts becauſe they haue not knowne my waies.</hi> Ignorance was the natural mother that brought the Iewes ſo many goodly ſins, and filled their Countrey with ſinners, or elſe Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> hath done them wrong, <hi>You are deceiued not knowing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Math.</hi> 22. Ignorance made them crucifie the Lord of Life, or elſe Saint <hi>Luke</hi> hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reached himſelfe, <hi>Actes</hi> 3.15. It was ignorance that made them become proud <hi>Iuſticiaries,</hi> depending wholly and relying vpon their owne righteouſneſſe, becauſe they knew not the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:5459:54"/>righteouſneſſe of God, or elſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath cenſured them too hard, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. Ignorance was the blind guide that led the Gentiles to idolatry, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.8. And Ignorance of things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God, ſet <hi>Paules</hi> head on working of miſchiefe againſt the Church of God, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. and this is a diſeaſe ſo infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that it poyſons whatſoeuer good thing lies in the ſame womb with it: It poyſons Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion with Idolatry; it infects de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion and zeale with ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; it makes hope to ſwell with preſumption; and turnes euery ſymptome of feare into deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and horrour:<note place="margin">Cauſa cauſa &amp; cauſa cauſati.</note> And if Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke that is old bee not worne quite out of date, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ignorance which is proued and conuicted to be the prime cauſe of ſin, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but vſher and make
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:5459:54"/>way for puniſhment. I appeale for proofe to the Oracles of God, where I finde it puniſhed ſometimes with captiuity, <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.13. <hi>My people is gone into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity becauſe they wanted know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:</hi> Sometimes with deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Eſay</hi> 27. Sometimes with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.6. It maketh ſubiect to the curſe. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 79.6. It maketh ſtrangers from the life of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18. It debarres from the life of glory: For they that know not one foote of the way to heauen, how is it poſſible they ſhould paſſe through ſo many winding <hi>Maeanders,</hi> and perplexed paſſages, vnto thoſe fortunate Ilands of ineffable comfort? Laſtly, Ignorance ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth lyable to the vengeance of God in the day of iudgement, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Hee ſhall come in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire to render vengeance
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:5459:55"/>vnto them that know not God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore the more to blame was the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> for ſetting lock &amp; key vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Scriptures, that the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie might not look into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but with as great and eminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger as the men of <hi>Bethſhemeſh</hi> for looking into the Arke, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. and <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth Pope of that name,<note place="margin">Pius <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> for cenſuring the ſacred Oracles of Heauen amongſt bookes prohibited, marking them in the fore-head with the ſtroke of <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> God hath not dedicated the Bible to the Laitie;<note place="margin">Hoſius.</note> and of <hi>Hoſius</hi> a father in the <hi>Trent</hi> conſpiracie, that it is fitter for women to meddle with the Diſtaffe, then with the word of God. Suffer me to draw a little bloud out of this veine; for whatſoeuer they doe or can pretend, it is euident out of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:5459:55"/>Stories that in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church the word of God was not onely permitted to the Lay people to reade, but alſo that tranſlations were prouided of ſet purpoſe, that they might reade it. We reade in <hi>Socrates,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Socrat. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi>
                     </note> that they were tranſlated by <hi>Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philas</hi> Biſhop of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> that the Barbarians might learne them; by <hi>Methodius</hi> into the <hi>Slauonian</hi> tongue.<note place="margin">Chryſ. Hom. <hi>1.</hi> in Iohan.</note> S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his firſt Homily vpon <hi>Iohn,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members the <hi>Syrian,</hi> the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> the <hi>Indian,</hi> the <hi>Perſian,</hi> the <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> and many others: And <hi>Theodoret</hi> in his firſt Booke,<note place="margin">Theod. de curan. Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectibus lib. <hi>15.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>De curandis Graecorum affectibus,</hi> will beare vs witneſſe that in his time the Bible was turned into all Languages in the world; &amp; what one thing is more common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Fathers, then often to bee calling vpon the people to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:5459:56"/>get themſelues Bibles, to reade and examine them: Then the Laitie was acquainted with the Text of Scripture as well as the learned, and then the doctrine of <hi>Hoſius</hi> was not hatched: So we reade in <hi>Socrates,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Socr. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> of <hi>Nectari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> that of a Iudge, and one of the Laitie, he was made Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> by the conſent of an 150 Biſhops; And of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Socrat. l. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi>
                     </note> who was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated from the gouernement of a Prouince to bee Biſhop of <hi>Millain:</hi> Of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the father of <hi>Nazianzene;</hi> Of <hi>Thalaſsim,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> that from pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men, they were remoued to ſit at the ſterne of the Church; which ſhewes how painefull and how indefatigably diligent they had bene in the Word of God, and in the ſearch of Scriptures, that being but Lay-men, yet
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:5459:56"/>were ſuppoſed able to ſuſtaine the office &amp; charge of Biſhops. Wee reade in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. eccleſ. l. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> that hee was trained vp in the Scriptures from a child, that hee got them without booke, and was wont to queſtion with his father <hi>Leonides</hi> about the difficult meaning of ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Of <hi>Macrina</hi> foſter mother to S. <hi>Baſil,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Baſil. Epiſt <hi>74.</hi>
                     </note> that ſhee propoſed vnto her ſelfe the example of <hi>Timothy,</hi> and trained him vp in learning the Scriptures from his infancy. S. <hi>Baſil</hi> himſelfe is our recorder in his 74. Epiſtle; ſo wee reade in <hi>Nicephorus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Niceph. lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </note> his 8. booke and 14. chapter, of <hi>Paphnuſius</hi> a Lay-man, and yet ſo renowmed for his ſingular knowledge in Diuinitie, that he was accounted worthy to beare a part, and be no ſmall helper in the Councell of <hi>Nice:</hi> And who
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:5459:57"/>knowes not that S. <hi>Hierome</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects many of his Epiſtles vnto godly women,<note place="margin">Hierom.</note> highly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them for their labour in the Scriptures? Or who knowes not that S. <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelfe writ his ſecond Epiſtle to his elect La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy?<note place="margin">Ioh. Epiſt. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> which Epiſtle is Canonicall Scripture: And is it not a ſhame to thinke that hee would ſend her an Epiſtle which ſhe might not reade? It was indeed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach which <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata obiected againſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; and from him it ſeemes that <hi>Hoſius</hi> and <hi>Andradius,</hi> and our blinde <hi>Romiſh</hi> guides haue borrowed it: By all which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, that this muffling of mens eyes, which the <hi>Trent</hi> men haue deuiſed, is but a noueltie and a trick to win ſome credit to their Legend, thevery ſhop and forge of lies; and vnder the vaile
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:5459:57"/>and miſt of Ignorance, to ſend whole droues and legions of ſoules to hell. But for you (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) I ſhall beſeech God in the words of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and I beſeech you vſe the ſame prayer for your ſelues; <hi>That the word of God may dwell in you plentifully in all Wiſedome;</hi> that the booke of God may neuer bee wreſted out of your hand; that hee would open to you the treaſures of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge, which there are hid; that you may bee like <hi>Apollos</hi> powerfull, and like <hi>Tertullus</hi> learned in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that you may relliſh that heauenly Manna, that you may long after the ſincere milk of the Goſpell, that you may performe indeed as much as God gaue <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> in charge, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1.8. That this booke of God may not depart out of your mouthes,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:5459:58"/>that you meditate therein day and night, that you obſerue and do all that is written therein; for thus you ſhall make your waies proſperous, you ſhall make your ſorrowes eaſie, your comforts many, your vertues eminent, your conſcience quiet, your life holy, your death comfortable, your election ſure, your ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on certaine; and ſo I make poſte haſte to thoſe fiue ſins which I called <hi>poſitiue,</hi> whereof the firſt is ſwearing.</p>
                  <p>Swearing,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1 Poſitiue ſin.</hi> Zanchius. Polanus. Mercer. Ribera <hi>out of</hi> Hier. Error Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nich. &amp; Anabap. Zanchius in <hi>3.</hi> praeceptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex Gratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</note> the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word <hi>Aloh</hi> may either ſignifie curſing and execration, as <hi>Zanchius;</hi> or Periury, and foreſwearing, as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus;</hi> or ſlandering &amp; detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as <hi>Mercer</hi> would haue it. I rather follow the expoſition of <hi>Ribera</hi> out of Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> that here it is vſed to ſignifie raſh &amp; idle ſwearing; ſo that heere is no
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:5459:58"/>ſhroud for that doting humour of Anabaptiſts, and Manichees, which they wold gladly reare &amp; build out of the fift of <hi>Mathew, Sweare not at all:</hi> and out of the fift of <hi>Iames</hi> the 12. <hi>My brethren aboue all things ſweare not. Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> (ſaith <hi>Zanchius</hi> in his expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon the third commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) will helpe vs with a lifte out of the Fathers to anſwere them, <hi>Damnantur à Chriſto, &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolo iuramenta temeraria, quae vulgo habentur in colloquijs, non ea quae coram Magiſtratu habentur in iudicijs.</hi> Our Sauiour forbids common and idle ſwearing in our ordinary talke &amp; vpon ſlight occaſion, but he forbids not the lawfull vſe of an oath before the Magiſtrate, which elſe-where hee allowes, and cals the Iudge and <hi>Palaemon</hi> to make an end of all contention, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16. This
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:5459:59"/>then needs muſt bee the point.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Raſh and idle ſwearing being not performed, in iuſtice, in truth, and in iudgement, is ſuch a ſinne as will make a whole Land to mourne and ſhake.</hi> The truth whereof is moſt apparant in the 23 of <hi>Ieremy</hi> at the 10. <hi>Becauſe of oathes the Land mourneth:</hi> To which we may adde that blacke doome gone out againſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſwearers in the fift of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary, The curſe of God ſhall lay ſiege vnto the houſe of him that ſweareth, vntill it haue conſumed the timber, and the ſtones thereof:</hi> And that ſentence of <hi>Syracides, Eccle.</hi> 23.11. <hi>He that vſeth ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſhall bee filled with wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the plague ſhall neuer be remoued from his houſe.</hi> It ſeemes this doctrine hath beene long known and Preached, &amp; this ſin alſo cried downe by the ancient
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:5459:59"/>Lawes of moſt Nations in the world:<note place="margin">Iohannes Boaemus de moribus Gentium lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> Boamus l. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> for amongſt the <hi>Egiptians</hi> whoſoeuer was conuicted for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſwearer was to looſe his head: amongſt the <hi>Scythians</hi> it was the loſſe &amp; forfeiture of all his goods: amongſt the <hi>Romanes</hi> the ſwearer was to bee throwne with violence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the top of the rock <hi>Tarpeius.</hi> And this was the cauſe (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi>) that they would not ſuffer their children to ſweare by the name of <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> within dores,<note place="margin">Quaeſt. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam.</note> but enioyned them to go abroad, and there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate of their oaths. Amongſt the <hi>Grecians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Graeci.</note> the ſwearer was to looſe his eares:<note place="margin">Iudaei in Talmud.</note> the <hi>Iewes</hi> were wont to rent their cloaths when they heard the name of God prophaned; which if we ſhould do in our daies, we ſhould rent our cloathes ſo oft as wee heare men ſpewing black and fearfull
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:5459:60"/>oathes, one ſuite would not laſt vs one day; nay, ſometimes not hang ſo long vpon our backes, till our fleſh or skinnes were warme within vs. Yea, the very Turkes,<note place="margin">Boaemus de moribus Gentium lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note> as ſome report of them, will ſtop their eares at the hearing of an oath. And it is memorable of one of the Kings of France,<note place="margin">Rhenan in annot. in Tertul.</note> who (as <hi>Beatus Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanus</hi> records) made this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute; that Swearers ſhould haue their mouthes ſeared with bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning irons. And one of the Kings of this Land, out of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious care to preuent the doome which the heauens threatned for this ſin; ordained that a mulet and forfeiture ſhold be exacted of euery one that was heard or noted to ſweare within his Court. To ſhut vp this proofe, ſwearing is a ſinne that brings the wrath of God, not
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:5459:60"/>only vpon the party that ſwears though he be ſure not to eſcape, nor only vpon the houſe where he dwels, as the ſinne of <hi>Ely</hi> for want of due correction vpon <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehas:</hi> but vpon the country, as the ſin of <hi>Achan</hi> brought wrath vpon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the ſin of the men of <hi>Gibeah,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded the ruine of the whole tribe of <hi>Beniamin, Iudg.</hi> 20. &amp; yet woe be vnto vs, for our land may truely take vp that mournefull complaint of the Prophet <hi>Eſay, The whole Land is ſicke, and the whole heart is heauy with this ſin:</hi> and redouble often and often the Elegie of <hi>Ieremy: Becauſe of Oathes our Land mourneth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our Magiſtrates that ſhould put bridles in the lips of others,<note place="margin">Magiſtrats tainted with this ſinne.</note> doe not, or elſe they dare not, make anie Lawes againſt this ſinne, for feare leſt they ſhould
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:5459:61"/>proue nets to catch themſelues. Moſt of our noble ſtemmes,<note place="margin">The No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</note> to ſhew their vndanted boldneſſe, (in open railing vpon God him ſelfe) do ſhew more baſe corage in out-vying of oaths then euer they are like to doe in martiall feates in Armes. GOD hath vouchſafed to houor them more then others, and they diſhon or him, &amp; endanger the honour of this land, as much as any. Thoſe that ſhould proue the hope and life of the Gentry,<note place="margin">The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</note> make it the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall &amp; common figure in their Rhetorike, not to giue their beſt friend a word, til firſt they haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of God a wound; an oth is the proeme of all their ſpeeches, &amp; compleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their diſcourſe; there is not the leaſt errour in caſting of a die, but it muſt coſt our Sauiour a ſtab; he will not looſe one penny by his
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:5459:61"/>gaming, but Chriſt Ieſus muſt pay for it, it ſhall coſt him the ſtaining and impeachment of his deareſt houour; if his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour wrong him, although but in ſhew, by fearefull oathes he will be reuenged on GOD for that; if GOD will be ſo merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as to crowne him with ſome vnexpected bleſſing, then hee ſhews his contentment with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cads and pages of oathes. This is the Dialect wherein GOD muſt be thanked for that, it is moſt true of them which <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilian lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Inſtit.</hi> ſaid of his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pill: <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum prima exprimit ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, etiam iurare didicit:</hi> an oath is the firſt Engliſh which he lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth; <hi>Et qui iurat cum repit quid non adultus faciet?</hi> If they can ſweare in their cradles, they will ſhake a Land with oathes when they are old.<note place="margin">Citizens.</note> Our Citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:5459:62"/>ſhold be ſamplars for the world to imitate, will not ſticke to ſell their ſouls, ſo they may ſell their wares with it: but is it not a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and ſory bargain, when for euery trifling gaine, not worth the naming, they giue their ſouls to boot, which cannot be redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with a thouſand worlds. If you chance to come neere the Court,<note place="margin">Courtiers.</note> you would thinke you were entred vpon a ſtage, and come into a ſchoole of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: if you walke into the ſtreets of the city, you would think you were among the courtiers ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, who hauing often heard their lectures of ſwearing, were now boldly &amp; readily repeating them. Caſt eye vpon the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſwaine,<note place="margin">Country-men.</note> and there is not the ſillieſt catiffe, howſoeuer defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of all the endowments both of grace and nature, but is wiſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:5459:62"/>enough to practiſe this ſinne; he that by nature is moſt rude and barbarous in ſpeaking, can be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent &amp; rhetorical enough in ſwearing, that howſoeuer they are excelled by Courtiers and Citizens in varietie of attire, yet they diſdain &amp; ſcorne, that they ſhould put them downe, eyther in the complement &amp; brauery, or in the variety of new faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned oathes. Thus do men of all eſtates turne worſe then Iewes, in crucifying the Lord of glory, &amp; ripping their Sauiors wounds to bleede againe; for the Iewes crucified him but once, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſwearer, thou crucifieſt him almoſt at euery word thou ſpeakeſt; the Iewes ſinned of ignorance, not knowing that he was the Meſſias, but thou of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe; the Iewes called for <hi>Pilate</hi> to crucifie him, but thou
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:5459:63"/>vngracious murtherer wilt do it thy ſelfe, and inſtead of croſſe &amp; nailes, thou renteſt and grindeſt him to pieces betwixt thy teeth. This dreadfull name of God, &amp; this ſweete name of Ieſus, is all the Euidence, and all the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thou haſt to ſhew, for thy right and title in heauen. If this preuayle not, thou art a ſparke of Tophet, and a fire-brand of Hell: and wilt thou for all this, teare in peeces this dreadfull name? wilt thou rent thy owne Charter, and by blotting this name, blot thy owne name out of the booke of Life? Suppoſe there could not be found any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſin in all our Land, ſuppoſe ſwearing had not any other ſin to bear it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, ſuppoſe there were no forraine enemy in the world to annoy or inuade vs, yet the frequent vſe of this infernall
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:5459:63"/>dialect and language of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, would prooue an engine and rampire ſtrong enough to batter our walles, a ſword keene enough to martyr our fleſh, an arrow ſwift enough to drinke vp our bloud, a diſeaſe ſharpe and deſperate enough, to make a flawe in our eſtate, a breach in our peace, and a ſcarre in our Church, a ſhaking ague, and hot feuer, ſure enough to ſhake our Land from one end vnto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and therefore, if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and tender the peace and welfare of this kingdome; if you beare any loue to this Nation, if you affect the health of <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> if you wiſh from your harts that the floriſh and happines of our ſtate &amp; land may be immortall, if you haue any zeale or corage for the Lord of Hoſts, then gird your ſwords vpon your thighs,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:5459:64"/>arme your ſelues with courage &amp; reſolution, to ſtop the mouth of this crying ſin: It is a proud ſin, that ſcornes to quarrell with any vnder God himſelfe: It is a ſtowt ſin, that is alway heauing at the ſtrength &amp; foundation of our Land. O ſuffer it not to walk in your ſtreetes, to ſitte at your boards, to tary in your ſhops to jet in your Markets without a check: why ſhould this aboue all other ſins ſtoope and ſubmit it ſelfe to no law? why ſhould this aboue al other ſins be ſubiect to no cenſure? O that ſome good <hi>Phinehas</hi> who is zealous of the name of God, would breake vs the ice, and take in hand to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe &amp; procure from our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, ſome wholſome law, ſome ſharpe and cutting ſtatute, that might ſnape the growth, and ſtanch the bloody fluxe of this
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:5459:64"/>hainous impiety; verily GOD would ſay of ſuch a man as hee ſaid of <hi>Phinehas, Numb.</hi> 25. This good man that was zealous for my ſake, hath turned away mine anger from you; ſurely happie ſhould be that day, and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſhould be the memorie, and honoured for euer ſhould bee that man, by whoſe zealous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours ſo good a work ſhould bee effected; their memories ſhould neuer periſh, but where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer there ſhould be but me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their names, there alſo the good worke that they haue done, ſhould be ſpoken of for a memoriall of them; and would God wee might be ſo happie as once to ſee that day. And ſo I come to the ſecond ſin, which is <hi>Lying,</hi> wherein I dare paſſe my word I will be briefe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cacheſh,</hi> howſoeuer in <hi>Kal,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d poſitiue ſinne.</note> it
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:5459:65"/>may ſignifie to wax faint, and be without courage, yet in <hi>Piel,</hi> as here it is vſed, it ſignifies to lie; &amp; is by <hi>Martyr</hi> out of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> defined to be either <hi>the vttering of ſome vntruth, or the vttering of a truth vntruly, with intent and purpoſe to deceiue. Aquinas ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ſecundae</hi> in his 110. queſtion,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de mendacio.</note> makes eight kinds of lies, but S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> more conciſely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes them al in three. The firſt for profit, which is called <hi>officio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum;</hi> another for merime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which is called <hi>iocoſum;</hi> the third of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, which he calls <hi>pernicioſum.</hi> The firſt kind of lie takes hold of thoſe, that for a little lucre ſend truth a packing. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d takes hold of thoſe, who affecting to make others ſport, ſet their wits on working. The third taks hold of thoſe, that vſe to whet their tong with gall, to wreacke their
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:5459:65"/>malice. And there is none of theſe, eyther ſo mincing or ſo neate and handſome, but it is a foule &amp; lothſome ſin. For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer <hi>Plato</hi> in his ſecond Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue <hi>de Republica;</hi> and <hi>Quinti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> in his twelfth Booke of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions; and <hi>Aquinas</hi> in the place beforecited, at the 4. Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, can finde in their hearts to wink at ſuch lies as are ful of wit and good conceit; and S. <hi>Ierome</hi> himſelfe, would father ſome of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious lies, euen vpon the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, from the example of the Egiptian Midwiues, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1. and of <hi>Rahab, Ioſhua</hi> 2. and of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Gen.</hi> 12. and of <hi>Iacob, Gen.</hi> 27. Yet ſeeing S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> a better ſcholler then <hi>Plato;</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> a better Oratour then <hi>Quintili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an;</hi> and both <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Commentators then eyther <hi>Aquinas,</hi> or Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi> as I
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:5459:66"/>hope wil take my part, I ſhal not ſhrinke nor retract what I haue ſaid; that there is no kind of lie, be it neuer ſo neately trimd, and wittily contriued,<note place="margin">All ſorts of lies be ſinnes.</note> neuer ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to proue good and aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, which may not without any ſlander be cenſured and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a ſinne.</p>
                  <p>For proofe whereof, I might appeale to the Eſſaei among the <hi>Iewes</hi> in <hi>Euſebius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Euſeb. de praep. Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel. lib. <hi>8</hi>
                     </note> his 8. Booke <hi>de Preparatione Euangelica,</hi> and 4. cha. to <hi>Damaſcene</hi> in the 3. of his Paralels: to <hi>Chytraeus</hi> in a Tract <hi>de Iacobi mendacio:</hi> to <hi>Gerſon</hi> in his proteſtation about the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith: to Saint <hi>Bernard de modo bene viuendi,</hi> 31. Sermon: Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who of ſet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe hath anſwered S. <hi>Ierome</hi> in his 8. and 9. Epiſtles: to the laws of the <hi>Perſians</hi> in <hi>Plutarch:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plutarch. de vitando.</note> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit other authorities. But when
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:5459:66"/>the Scriptures be plaine, I liſt to ſeeke no further. Shall <hi>Salomon</hi> then be iudge? I am contented, vpon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition he may be heard to ſpeake out of the 12. of the <hi>Prouerbs</hi> v. 22. for there he hath defined a lie to be abomination in the fight of God. Or if you wil heare him ſpeake out of the 6. of <hi>Prouerbs</hi> v. 17. for there hee hath pictured a lie with this mot to vpon the face: <hi>The ſin which God abhorreth.</hi> Which place is not meant onely of the pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lie, which is ſpiced with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice; but alſo of merry &amp; concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lies. For otherwiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> hath thwarted <hi>Hoſea,</hi> who blackt it on the head for a ſin, to make Princes merry with lies, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 7.3. not only of the pernicious lie, that is lined and bolſtered with gall and rancor, but alſo of the officious and profitable lie: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:5459:67"/>
                     <hi>Salomon</hi> forgot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, when he commands, that vpon no tearmes, that vpon no conditions, we ſhould make ſale of truth, <hi>Pro.</hi> 23. If any lie might merit or pleade not guilty, then ſurely it ſhould be ſuch a one, as maketh for the defence and encreaſe of Gods glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, &amp; yet euen this lie alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues an <hi>Anathema,</hi> from the 13 of <hi>Iob</hi> v. 7.9. <hi>will you lie for Gods defence? Is it well that one ſhould make a lie for him?</hi> The modell of time will not abide any profuſe or large diſcourſe, I therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitomize and contract my lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger meditations into this briefe ſumme. The pernicious lie which is of malice, as it hath no father but the diuell, ſo hath it no other Patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to defend it: the lie for ſport and merriment wee haue already diſabled; and the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:5459:67"/>ground of the officious lie is but a quick-ſand, vnable to ſupport ſuch a weighty ſin. For ſay thou lie to helpe thy neighbour at a dead lift, perhaps to ſaue his life, a thing that God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands, this is but a weak ſupporter; for euen in this thou doſt thy ſelfe more hurt, then thou canſt doe thy neighbour good, <hi>Niſi fiat iuſtis &amp; rectis medijs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. Martyr de menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio.</note> ſaith <hi>Martyr</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be done by lawfull and warrantable means. Say thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the benefit of the Church, and by conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Gods greater glory; yet S. <hi>Paul</hi> will ſchoole thee better, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1. Thou maiſt not giue way to the ſmalleſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, in hope of the greater good to follow thereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If it be obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that the <hi>Egiptian</hi> midwiues lied, and God bleſſed them; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that God bleſſed them not for the lie, but for their faith that
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:5459:68"/>wrought in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by loue. If it be ſaid that <hi>Abraham</hi> lied to <hi>Pharao,</hi> and to <hi>Abimelech.</hi> I anſwer, it is more then can be prooued. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he ſaid that <hi>Sarah</hi> was his ſiſter, &amp; it was true; for they were the children of the ſame father, but not of the ſame mother, as <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelfe expounds his owne meaning, <hi>Ge.</hi> 20.12. but he neuer denied that ſhee was his wife; <hi>Non petit Abraham vt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah mentiatur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iunius, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> deſired her not to lie: what then? S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in his 22. booke againſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the <hi>Maniche,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aug. contra Fauſt. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic. lib. <hi>22.</hi>
                     </note> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres it thus: <hi>Veritatem voluit celari, non mendacium dici:</hi> he bid her not ſpeake a word but truth, and yet be warie that ſhe tolde not all that ſhee knew, <hi>à nemine enim id exigitur vt totum depro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat quod nouit; Phar ao</hi> could not bind them to reueale the whole
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:5459:68"/>truth, ſaith <hi>Martyr,</hi> in aſſoyling of this doubt. If it bee ſaid that <hi>Iacob</hi> lyed when hee told his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he was his elder ſonne <hi>Eſau; Aquinas</hi> anſwereth, <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ſecundae quaeſt.</hi> 110. <hi>Artic.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Aquinus <hi>2.</hi> a. <hi>2.</hi> ae. q. <hi>110.</hi> Art. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> that the ſaying was myſticall not vntrue, as if he ſhould haue ſaid; I am the elder by grace; or thus, it was Prophetical to ſhew a myſterie; <hi>Quod minor populus hoc eſt Gentium ſubſtituendus eſſet in locum primogeniti hoc eſt Iudae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum;</hi> By <hi>Eſau</hi> he meant the <hi>Iews,</hi> by himſelfe the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and his purpoſe was to ſignifie that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the <hi>Iewes</hi> were Gods firſt borne, yet they ſhould bee caſt off, and the Gentiles who were the yonger brethren, were they to whom the bleſſing and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance did belong. But I will dwell no longer on this point. The cloſure is this, <hi>Si quando lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuti
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:5459:69"/>ſunt vt homines, peccaſſe non diffitebimur:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. Martyr. in locis com. de menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio.</note> If they ſpeake theſe things as men they erred, and we denie it not: <hi>Sin veró af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flatu Dei, mirabimur e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rum dicta ſed in exemplum non trahemus:</hi> If theſe things were ſpoken by the motion and direction of Gods Spirit, wee will ſtand in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wiſedome of God; yet dare wee not make this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe a patterne for vs to imitate, but for all lies we will make bold there to include them, where the day of iudgement without repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance will be ſure to finde them, euen in the Catalogue &amp; amidſt the bedrole of our ſinnes. Set a watch therefore before thy mouth, and keep the dore of thy lips, that thou vtter not a lie; ſet lock &amp; key vpon thy eares, that thou entertaine not the voyce of him that telleth a lie. For as
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:5459:69"/>he that telleth the lie, hath the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel in his tongue; ſo he that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the lie hath the deuill in his eare, and quickly it creeps in at the eare that wil neuer out of the heart while thy breath is in thee.</p>
                  <p>The time hath already com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me to take my work out of the Loomes, and to let the other three ſins remaine vntou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; would God they were alſo left vnpractiſed: nay, it were wel if they were not alſo profeſſed amongſt you. This (beloued) this is the only thing that we the Miniſters òf God, who come here to ſpend our breath, would gladly beg, this onley is the thing that wee would faine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech with all the bowels of our affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, with our eyes watring, with our fleſh ſhaking, with our hearts bleeding, with our ſoules mourning, with al the ſtrings of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:5459:70"/>our hearts enlarged towards you, that you would not ſuffer theſe ſins to dwell amongſt you, that now at length you would draw your ſwords againſt ſinne, which at euery corner beſiegeth your Citie, before it beginne to batter your wals. It is a craſtie <hi>Sinon,</hi> you cannot lodge it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your gates but with feare and danger of your liues; it is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted rebell againſt heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, you may not harbour it, it is a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed traitor againſt the peace and quiet of your Land, you cannot entertaine it without ſuſpition of high treaſon both againſt our bleſſed Sauiour, &amp; our gracious Soueraigne. Alas beloued, how long, how long, ſhall the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher cry that ſin is more to bee feared then any treaſon, and yet we practiſe it? How long ſhall the Preacher cry that ſin is the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:5459:70"/>onely <hi>Troyan-horſe,</hi> whoſe womb can command a bloudy <hi>Armado,</hi> armed with cruelty and rage to work our ouerthrow, and yet we entertaine and welcome it? how long ſhall the Preacher cry in our ſtreets, and wring it in your eares, that ſin is the onely make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate betwixt God and vs, &amp; yet wee are in league and compact with it? How long ſhal the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher proclaime this truth, that our Land will neuer bee rid of Prieſts and Ieſuites, the little Foxes that hinder the growth of the Goſpel, til firſt we haue cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down our ſin, and yet we will not leaue it? how long ſhall the Preacher cry, nay, weary the ſtrings of his tongue, and weary his ſides, and breake the veines and the pipes of his heart, with crying that the ſin of our Land, that the ſinne of our people, and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:5459:71"/>the vnthankfulneſſe of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hath taken away the glory and the mirrour of <hi>Princes,</hi> the ſtaffe of our comfort, the ioy of our heart, and the hope of our Land; and yet we dandle it on our knees, and yet wee foſter it: we would be lotheto beſtow our loue vpon him that ſhould pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe treaſon againſt the Crown, and yet we loue our ſin which is more treacherous: we would be loath to ſee our Land inuaded by forraine enemies that were ſtronger then wee, and yet wee keepe our ſin at home, which is more dangerous: ſurely our eies would ſink into their holes, and our haires ſtart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our heads, and our hearts would breake in ſunder within our ſides, if euer we ſhold heare of the ſubuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our State, of the ſacking of our Kingdome, of the downefall of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:5459:71"/>our Churches, of the burning of our houſes and Cities ouer our heads, of the eclipfe and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Goſpel amongſt vs: and yet alas our ſins are ſtirring the aſhes, &amp; blowing the coles, and putting oyle to the flame of Gods diſpleaſure, and how ſhall we quench it? we muſt quench it by a flood of teares, by watery eies, by bleeding hearts, by pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue ſoules; wee muſt quench it by making oureies fountains, &amp; our heads ſprings, &amp; our hearts riuers of teares: nay, let vs euen turne our fountaine of teares in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtreame, and our ſtreame of teares into a floud, &amp; our floud of teares into an Ocean, and let that Ocean be bottomles, &amp; that ſpring boundleſſe, and that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of teares neuer be dried vp, that <hi>God</hi> may be pleaſed to heale our Land, which he hath ſhaken,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:5459:72"/>to renew our hopes which hee hath croſſed, to turne away the iudgement w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> hee hath threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to crowne vs with thoſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riads of bleſſings which he hath promiſed: and amongſt all theſe thy bleſſings, write downe theſe particular by name; Crown our gracious Soueraigne, and this Kingdome with immortall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe; let the Scepter neuer depart from his ſeed; let none of his ſeed euer depart away from thee: weaken the wals of <hi>Babel;</hi> continue the light of thy holy Goſpell; bleſſe our friends; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert, or elſe confound, or infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate ourfoes; kindle our zeale; ſoften our hearts; heale our fores; pardon our ſinnes; ſaue our ſoules at the laſt day, for thy Son Chriſt Ieſus his ſake.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5459:72"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5459:73"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5459:73"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Englands</hi> SECOND SVMMONS.</p>
                  <p>A Sermon Preached <hi>at Paules Croſſe the</hi> 5. of February, <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1615.</p>
                  <p>By THOMAS SVTTON Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelour of Diuinity, then Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of Queenes Colledge in Oxford, and now Preacher at S. <hi>Mary Oueries.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond Impreſſion, Peruſed and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Authour.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>REV. 3.19.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Be zealous and repent.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by NICHOLAS OKES for MATTHEVV LAVV, and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, at the Signe of the Fox. 1616.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:5459:74"/>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:5459:74"/>
                  <head>ENGLANDS SECOND <hi>Summons</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>REV. 3.15.16.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>I know thy workes, that thou art neither cold nor hote: I would thou wereſt either cold or hote.</p>
                        <p>Therefore, becauſe thou art luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme, and neither cold nor hote, it will come to paſſe, that I ſhall ſpue thee out of my mouth.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS whole chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter containes in it three Epiſtles en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited by God in the conſiſtory of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:5459:75"/>Heauen, ſent by his faithfull ſeruant <hi>Iohn,</hi> vnto three famous Churches of <hi>Aſia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Euery Epiſtle may be broken into foure quarters.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>firſt,</hi> an <hi>Exordium,</hi> or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance: The <hi>ſecond</hi> a generall propoſition: The <hi>third</hi> a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: The <hi>fourth</hi> an Epilogue or concluſion.</p>
                  <p>My <hi>Text</hi> is part of the laſt Epiſtle, directed to the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> whoſe <hi>Exordium,</hi> or entrance, is ſet downe in the 14 verſe; wherein I note.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> the party to whom this Epiſtle was directed, it is <hi>the Angell of the Church of Laodicea.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> the party greeting or ſending, it is <hi>Amen; God bleſſed for euer.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Propoſition in the 15 verſe, <hi>I know thy workes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Natration from the 15.
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:5459:75"/>verſe to the 22. The Epilogue and cloſure, verſe the laſt.</p>
                  <p>In the narration I diſcouer foure particulars.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Firſt, I find her checkt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended for her luke-warme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, verſ. 15.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, I finde her chid and threatned, verſe ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene.</item>
                     <item>Thirdly, I heare here her exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to more heate and ſeruencie in zeale, verſ. 19.</item>
                     <item>Laſtly, I ſee her intreated and allured by a gracious promiſe, verſe 20.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And ſurely this ſickneſſe of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> was a ſickneſſe vnto death, ſeeing the moſt ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne ſprigs of balm which the Phiſition could find in al <hi>Gilead,</hi> were not ſufficient to aſſwage her griefe, or mittigate her pain.</p>
                  <p>If you long to ſee the breaking
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:5459:76"/>vp of my Text into ſmaller fractions. In it you may obſerue:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, a prerogatiue royall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated onely vnto God, <hi>I know thy workes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, the deplored e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of theſe <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you haue: Firſt, the crime which was obiected, <hi>Thou art neither hote nor cold:</hi> Secondly, the aggrauation of the crime, by comparing Luke-warme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in religion with another ſin damnable in it ſelfe, yet par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable in reſpect of this: <hi>Would God thou wereſt either hote or cold.</hi> Thirdly, the ſentence of male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction which hee paſſed vpon them; <hi>Therefore I will ſpue thee out of my mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thus haue I briefly and courſely made my firſt draught, whereby you may gueſſe at the limbes, and gather
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:5459:76"/>the proportion of my whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
                  <p>Now if God ſhall continue his gracious aſſiſtance, and you your chriſtian attention; I ſhall imploy my beſt end euours, for this modell of time, to expreſſe the perfect feature of euerie member, beginning with that prerogatiue royall, which none can iuſtly clayme, but GOD. <hi>I know thy workes;</hi> as if in fuller tearmes hee had ſpoken thus: thou doeſt but feede thy ſelfe with vaine and fruitleſſe hopes, thou thinkeſt thou haſt done me good ſeruice by kneeling in my houſe, and hearing of my word, and by a tolerable care in the outward obſeruance of my Lawes; but for thy loue thou haſt eſpouſed that vnto the world, for thine affection thou haſt wedded that vnto
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:5459:77"/>thine <hi>Herodias,</hi> for thy zeale thou haſt enflamed that with the loue of thy owne wanton <hi>Dalilah:</hi> thou boweſt in mine houſe, but thou worſhippeſt <hi>Rimmon:</hi> thou profeſſeſt my name, but thou ſerueſt thine owne belly: thou runneſt for a Crowne, but thou lookeſt backe like <hi>Atalanta,</hi> and reacheſt at thoſe balls of Gold which the Diuell like a craftie <hi>Hippomenes</hi> hath ſcattered in the way. In the time of peace thou lookeſt faire, like the Curtaines of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> or the Apples of <hi>Sodome;</hi> but if I nurture thee neuer ſo lightly with my rodde of corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I finde thee blacke as Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar, and rotten as the Clay in the depth of winter: thou pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that my name may be hallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, but thou ſweareſt raſhly, and thou thinkeſt I he are thee
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:5459:77"/>not: thou committeſt adulterie with all thy louers, and thou thinkeſt that the night and the darkeneſſe ſhall be a Canopie to hide thee that I ſee thee not: thou grindeſt the faces of the poore for whom I died: thou vndermineſt the little Church which I haue planted, and thou thinkeſt that I know it not: but alaſſe for thee, the ſtrength of thy witte hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed thy ſinne, for there is not a thought ſo ſecret, but I can tell it, not a cabbin ſo reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but I am in it, no cloſet ſo ſecure but I can open it, nor no worke ſo cunningly contriued and wrought, but I ſhall know it.</p>
                  <p>When thou draweſt the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to commit adultery, and ſayeſt, no eie ſeeth me; then am I ſtanding beſide thy bed, when
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:5459:78"/>thou art hammering and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triuing bloudie and treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble practiſes, and ſayeſt no care heareth me; then am I liftning within thy Cloſet: When thou art hiding the ſpoyles, vvhich thou haſt taken from the Church, and ſayeſt, no man can controule me; then am I look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee in the face, and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my rodde ouer thee. I am about thy paths, and about thy bedde, and I take notice of all thy wayes, <hi>I know all thy workes:</hi> which one minerall, contaynes moe fragments of ineſtimable treaſures, then can be gathered vp in ſo ſhort a time, I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelfe with the bare tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of one Pearle, which lies as it were aboue ground, obui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the eyes of euerie paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, deſcribed in theſe termes. <hi>There is no worke, no purpoſe ſo
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:5459:78"/>ſecret which is not open and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the eyes of God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">We can hide no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall not neede to be prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall in ſpending mine ovvne breath, or your attention, in propping ſuch a knowne and ancient Theoreme, I purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omitte the many fruitleſſe diſputations of <hi>Lombard</hi> in his firſt booke of Diſtinctions; and of <hi>Aquinas</hi> in the firſt of his Summes the foureteenth Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: onely thus much I muſt needes praemiſe; that there is in GOD a two-fold knowledge. The one ſpeciall, which in Schooles is tearmed the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Approbation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God is ſayd onely to know his owne ſonnes and children, and not the reprobates, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee reade, <hi>Matthew.</hi> 7.23. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from me yee wicked, I know you not.</hi> And <hi>Romans</hi> 11.2. God
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:5459:79"/>hath not caſt away his people, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which he knew before. The other generall, and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, whereby hee readeth the moſt retired thoughts, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret purpoſes both of the good and badde; as if hee had them noted in great and capitall cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters before his eies. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which is the knowledge of Approbation, pertayneth to the vnſearchable and eternall decree of Gods Predeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſtands farre enough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loofe out of my way. The other which is abſolute and generall, is now at the Barre, and readie to be tried.</p>
                  <p>Shall <hi>Moſes</hi> bee the Iudge? then heare him in the ſixth of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> at the fifth verſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Lord fawe the inward meanings of the heart. The heart is ſeated in a darkeſome
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:5459:79"/>cloſet walled round about with fleſh, ſwadled vp and couered with the richeſt hangings of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures wardrobe, ſo charily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, ſo ſhrouded with vails, that though thou beare it in thy boſome, though thou feede it with thine owne goods, though thou ſtudy to delight &amp; pleaſe it, though it be thine owne, yet if thou wouldeſt giue a world for a ſight, thou couldeſt not haue it. Yet neyther is the heart ſo cloſe impriſoned, but hee beholdeth, nor a thought ſo priuily conceiued, but hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrieth, nor a ſparke of luſt ſo ſoftly blowne and kindled, but hee diſcerneth, nor the ſmalleſt ſeede of vngodlineſſe, ſo warily couered, but hee reuealeth it. Shall wee be tryed by <hi>Salomon?</hi> Then heare him in the 1. Booke of <hi>Kings,</hi> chapter 8. and verſe 39
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:5459:80"/>
                     <hi>The Lord knoweth the hearts of all the ſonnes of men.</hi> Shall we be tryed by GOD himſelfe? Then heare him in the firſt book of <hi>Samuel,</hi> chapter 16. verſe 7. <hi>Man beholdeth the outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, but the Lord beholdeth the heart.</hi> Shall wee be tryed by <hi>Dauid?</hi> Then heare him in the firſt Booke of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the 28. verſe the 9. <hi>The Lord ſearcheth all hearts, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth all imaginations of the thoughts.</hi> O heare him in that paſſionate Ode, that hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled when the nefarious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of <hi>Abſalon,</hi> and <hi>Shimei,</hi> had almoſt broken his heart, <hi>pſalme</hi> 139. <hi>The Lord vnderſtandeth my thoughts before I haue conceiued them, he is about my paths, Vt quid foris perpetrem: to watch what I doe abroad, and about my bed: Vt quid priuatus cogitem: to obſerue
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:5459:80"/>what I doe at home, hee ſpieth out all my wayes:</hi> whereto the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hath ſuited his ſtile: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> all things are naked and open, or as it were anatomized, and cutte vppe before his eyes, for that is the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paules</hi> alluſion, in the fourth chapter and thirteenth verſe to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews.</hi> You ſhall find in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond book of the <hi>Kings</hi> and ſixt chapter that the King of <hi>Aram</hi> could neuer plot ſo ſecretly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but <hi>Iſrael</hi> got wit and notice of it. This <hi>Aram</hi> is a fitte Emblemeto reſemble vs, who can not entertaine a ſinfull thought, though ſlumbering vpon our beds, nor effect a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked purpoſe, though bolted in our lodging, when our Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes are cloſed, and our Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines drawne, but this eye of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:5459:81"/>heauen ſees it, writes it downe in the Booke of his Accounts, and at the laſt day will ſummon and warne our ſoules to a rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning for it, <hi>Pecces quocunque ſub axe, ſub Ioue ſemper eris.</hi> Though thou iourney to the lovveſt vault and dungeon of Hell to hide thy ſelfe in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of Tophet: yet ſtill ſhalt thou finde it moſt true which the Heathen Poet ſpake merrily of his <hi>Silenus.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Virg. Egl. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Ad Lunae luminae viſus eris.</hi> He knows what thou art dooing, better then thou canſt tell him, and therefore <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erius</hi> in his three and thirtieth of his <hi>Hirogliphicks,</hi> out of <hi>Cyril,</hi> and <hi>Eucherius</hi> wittily reſembles GOD by the picture of an eye, ſtanding vppon the toppe of a ſtaffe, the ſtaffe is the Embleme of his power &amp; Scepter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he gouernes, and the eie is
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:5459:81"/>the Embleme of his all-ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knowledge, whereby he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and pierceth into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecie of all hearts.</p>
                  <p>Which poynt (let it bee as ſtale and common as it will) would it once be learned, were able enough of it ſelfe, to ſnape the growth of all our ſinnes, and ſtanch the bloudie iſſue of all our impieties. It was the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Bernard</hi> in his book <hi>de Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſolitaria,</hi> and of wiſe <hi>Seneca</hi> in his 11. Epiſtle; <hi>Semper proponen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ante oculos vir bonus, vt tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam illo ſpectante viuamus, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam illo vidente faciamus.</hi> The honeſt heathen was of opinion, that no man would preſume to ſin, that had not ſome hope to eſcape vnſeene. Come hither &amp; learne, thou diſſembling hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite;<note place="margin">God ſeeth hypocrits.</note> 
                     <hi>Introrſum turpis ſpecioſus pelle decora:</hi> thou that coggeſt
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:5459:82"/>and dallieſt with GOD, come hither and learne, thou loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt like to a goodlie paynted Tombe, but within thou art li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with rottenneſſe and with corruption, and GOD hath ſpied it; thou makeſt the world beleeue, that thou art all zeale, that thou loueſt no houſe but the Church, no houſhold but the Saints, that thou honoureſt no maiſter but God, that thou longeſt for no home but Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that thou affecteſt no ioy but Spirituall, that thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt at no honour but immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall; and yet thou wilt take a bribe like <hi>Gehezi;</hi> Thou wilt grate the faces, and ſipe the purſes, and pare the liuings, and leaue deſolate the manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the poore without inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, and yet thinkeſt that no eye ſhall ſee thee. Alaſſe for
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:5459:82"/>thee, deplored Wight, wilt thou plow nothing but <hi>Akelda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> a field of blood, and ſowe nothing in it but <hi>Zizania,</hi> the tares of iniquitie, and ſtill thinke no eye ſhall ſee thee? Alaſſe for thee; wilt thou openly plight thy troth vnto God, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately wedde thy ſelfe vnto the world? wilt thou burne with zeale at the Church, and freeze at home? wilt thou diſpute and ſpeake for Chriſt, but fight and ſtriue againſt him? wilt thou beare a faire golden tongue in thy mouth, and a foule cankred heart in thy belly? wilt thou weare Chriſts Liuerie on thy backe, and weare the diuells fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, and the ſhreds of his ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in thy boſome? wilt thou ſpeake aloud, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>Lord make me a cleane heart, &amp; create a right ſpirit within me:</hi> but vnderneath
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:5459:83"/>ioyne praier with him in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, <hi>Da mihi fallere, da iuſtum, ſanctúmque videri, noctem pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; fraudibus obijce nubem:</hi> that is, be nothing leſſe indeed, then what thou ſeemeſt, and wouldſt be thought to be, and ſtil thinke that no eye ſhall ſee thee; wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and ſhameleſſe man, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thou not ſinne in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a man, and yet lie fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and weltring in ſinne, in the preſence and ſight of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Angells?</p>
                  <p>O Embleme of follie! Art thou aſhamed to ſinne in the ſight and preſence of a man, and yet lie rotting in ſinne, and tumbling in bloud, and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of vice, and murthering thy owne ſoule, before the face of a dreadfull and awfull God? Were it not altogether as good for thee to damne thy ſoule in
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:5459:83"/>the ſight of men, as in the view and ſight of God? What follie like to this, to watch and tend a poore ſoule without dores, and ſtabbe it behinde a curtayne? or what follie like this, to keepe thy ſoule well and carefully, when men ſee thee, but to wound it in ſecret? or what follie like this, to tender thy ſoule at the Church, and to damne it in thy Cloſet?</p>
                  <p>Let the vnchaſt wanton,<note place="margin">God ſees adulterers</note> and the adulterer by name remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this. Surely, thou of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther art one of <hi>Salomons</hi> fooles: and the Wiſe man hath drawne thy portrayture, <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> the 23. chapter, and 18. and 19. verſes, Thou feareſt nothing but the eyes of man, thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in thine heart, who ſeeth me? I am compaſſed about vvith darkeneſſe, the walls couer me,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:5459:84"/>whom need I to feare? <hi>Nulla eſt in rima,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eraſ. Dial.</note> 
                     <hi>nullus qui me exaudiat:</hi> The blacke and ſable hangings of the night haue beſpredde themſelues ouer me; either now or neuer, I may ſinne with ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, I ſhall wipe my mouth in the morning, and not be deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Not deſcried ſayeſt thou? then ſurely thou mayeſt be bold to ſinne, all will be well. But ſhalt thou not be deſcryed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede? Canſt thou make thy doore ſo faſt, that the arme of the Almightie, and all the ſtrength of heauen cannot open it? Is there any darknes ſo thicke and palpable that this <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the eyes of Heauen cannot ſpie thee thorow it?<note place="margin">Homerus.</note> Is there anie vaile ſo cloſe, that the Father of Lights, and deſcrier of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets cannot find it? I dare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume thou dareſt not thinke it,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:5459:84"/>for when thou haſt muſled thy face like <hi>Thamar,</hi> to take a ſhort and ſinfull pleaſure, and hid thy ſelfe like <hi>Sarah,</hi> behind the dore, or with <hi>Adam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the buſhes; or with <hi>Ionah,</hi> in the keele and belly of the ſhip, yet thou muſt ſay vnto thy God as <hi>Ahab</hi> ſaid vnto <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah,</hi> 1. Kings 21.20. <hi>Haſt thou found mee O mine enemy?</hi> Nay O God terrible and dreadfull thou haſt found mee? And then let mee aske thee in the ſame tearmes that the yong gallant in <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> asked his wanton Miſtreſſe, <hi>An non pudet id facere in conſpectu Dei, ac teſtibus San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis Angelis, quod pudet facere in conſpectu hominum?</hi> May not the Sunne bee aſhamed, and the Starres gloome, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens bee aſtoniſhed, to ſee the haire of thy head how it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:5459:85"/>the windowes of thy head how they ſlippe and ſinke into their holes; thy pulſes how they beate, thy fleſh how it ſhaketh, thy heart how it panteth, thy conſcience how it is perplexed; how it ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth, how it chaſeth it ſelfe for feare of miſcarrying and treſpaſiing before the Iudges of the world, which are but little Globes of earth, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of liuing clay; but if once the curtaines of heauen bee drawne, and the firmament hanged with blackes, and thou entrencht with ruinous and dampie wals, and none ſees thee but God, then thy conſcience fals faſt aſleepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, thy <hi>Herodian</hi> tels thee thou art too too fearefull, thy fleſh tels thee thou art too too baſhfull; nay, thou turneſt
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:5459:85"/>powerfull Orator thus to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thy owne ſelfe, that there is now no cauſe to feare: The eye which I feared is now ouer-caſt and ſurpriſed with ſleepe: the light which I doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is now ouer-ſhadowed and couered with darkeneſſe; the witneſſe which I ſuſpected, is now retired and out of ſight, none ſees but God, why then ſhould I feare? As if there were no feare of going to hell, but that a man ſhould ſee thee going, were intolerable; as if it were no ſhame to ſinne, but to bee deſcried and taken, were inexpiable; as if the ſinne it ſelfe were but a trifle, onely the want of cunning and neate conueyance, made it execrable; whereas all this while an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry God ſtands looking on thee, and an iron rod is ſhaken
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:5459:86"/>ouer thee, and a bottomeleſſe Tophet is gaping for thee. Alas for thee deplored wight; wilt thou make euery ſinnefull pleaſure a haulter to ſtrangle thee? and euery ſtrange fleſh a lure to take thee? Wilt thou preſſe out of euerie bunch of grapes a pond to drowne thee, becauſe thou canſt choake thy ſelfe in this ſilken halter, and poyſon thy ſelfe with this ſtrange lure, and yet eſcape the cenſure of men? Surely thy owne ſoule and conſcience, may ſeeme to bee the authour and pen-man of this, or the like ruthfull and paſſionate Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie. O wanton fleſh whom I am enforced to ſerue! O re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious carcaſe, whoſe priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I remaine! O ſinnefull bodie whoſe Tenant I am, and in whoſe wombe I dwell! Why
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:5459:86"/>doſt thou not ceaſe to kill mee? <hi>In ipſo ſcelere eſt ſupplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſceleris;</hi> It were euen as good for mee to bee wounded in the view and face of the world, as to bee preſt to death, and ſtifled in a corner: and as good for mee to bee hayled to the ſlaughter, and aſſaulted in the open field, as to bee murthered in a priuate chamber. What if no man ſee thee, yet God ſees thee? Who is greater then hee? What if no man charge thee, yet God can condemne thee? What if thou delude the Humane Conſiſtorie, and mans Tribunall, yet ſhouldſt thou tremble to treſpaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy God who is greater then hee. It was a pretty ſaying of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> in <hi>Seneca</hi> his 97. Epiſtle. <hi>Quid ſi tuta poſsint eſſe ſeelera, ſi ſecura eſſe non poſsint?
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:5459:87"/>vel quid prodeſt nocentibus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buiſſe latendi facultatem, cum latendi fiduciam non habent?</hi> If the ſinner bee hemmed and guarded with walles, and yet haue a conſcience to bait and to dog him: If the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton bee attended and cloathed with darkeneſſe, and yet haue a God to ſee and reuenge him, then where is his comfort? or how is he ſafer for ſinning in ſecret?</p>
                  <p>Remember this, corrupt <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hazi,</hi> that pocketeſt bribes in priuate: Remember this great Plotter of the world, that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt at a hungry preferment with more haſte then good ſpeed, by giuing and taking of pledges, to binde and confirme vnlawfull promiſes that are made in ſecret: and let vs all remember this, that our hearts
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:5459:87"/>muſt needes bee ſhameleſly ſinnefull, and our caſes vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſperate, and our end vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly miſerable, if wee dare flie in the face of God, and grieue his holy Spirit, and rip our Sauiours wounds, and ſtabbe his bleſſed ſides, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we haue the darkneſſe for a maske, and the night for a couering, and the wals for a defence, and God hath none to beare him witneſſe. It was a good Poſition of <hi>Boetius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Boaetius de conſolatione Philoſophie, lib. <hi>5.</hi> laſt proſe.</note> 
                     <hi>de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatione Philoſophiae,</hi> his fifth Booke and laſt Proſe, <hi>Magna eſt neceſsitas probitatis, cum agitis ante oculos, iudicis cuncta cernen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> A man cannot chuſe but bee good, who remembers that hee ſtands alwaies in the ſight of God: And therefore <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentius</hi> in one of his Hymnes giues this good memorandum,<note place="margin">Prudentius Himnorum l. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <pb n="164" facs="tcp:5459:88"/>
                     <hi>quicquid ages furtimuè, palamuè, memento inſpectatorem ſemper adeſſe Deum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And heere would I gladly make a ſtop, and ſtint my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in this point, but that I finde two of the beſt ſorts of men, that may iuſtly waite and expect ſome further vſe. The one would haue encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, the other would haue comfort from my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and I haue ſufficient to content them both. The one is hee that ſpendeth his breath and ſpirits in doing of good. The other is hee that is breatheleſſe alreadie, being almoſt diſconſolate, and out of heart, by ſuſtaining of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, each of them ſhall haue a taſte, leſt if I ſend them emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie home, the one ſhould bee diſcouraged, the other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:5459:88"/>in the way.</p>
                  <p>Giue mee a man that hath coped and buckled with the ſinnes of the time:<note place="margin">An incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to doe good.</note> Giue mee a man that hath ſtudied the aduancement of Religion; Giue mee a man that hath pleaded the Lords cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fauourites of <hi>Baal,</hi> as <hi>Elias</hi> did, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 18. That hath prouided for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did, 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 6. That ſhewes himſelfe zealous for the Lord of Hoſts, as <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> did, <hi>Numbers</hi> 25. at the 11. That hath encouraged thoſe that fight the battels of the Lord as <hi>Abigail</hi> did, the firſt of <hi>Samuel</hi> the 25. That hath reformed the contempt of the Sabboath, as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did, <hi>Nehem.</hi> the 13. the 22. and then tell mee what can be more auaileable to enflame his zeale,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:5459:89"/>to ſet edge vpon his affection, to make him Chriſtianly am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious in ſtriuing for heauen, to make him out-vie and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip his brethren, to make a man ſweate and tugge with more eagerneſſe and feruencie of ſpirit, in building of the houſe or prouoking the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt, then this one; that God ſees him, that the heauens applaude him, that God and Angels are ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, God and Angels atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants to grace and honour him? Was there euer ſpirit ſo dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous and baſe that will not ſtirre and ſtrike with violence, when the eye of his Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell is fixed full vpon him? And is there not as good reaſon, that the Chriſtian warriour ſhould march with a courage againſt ſinne, becauſe his
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:5459:89"/>Maiſter and Captaine Ieſus Chriſt neuer caſts his eie of him? If <hi>Elias</hi> bee pleading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Baal,</hi> this ſhould make him more hot and vehement; If <hi>Eliſha</hi> bee prouiding for the Prophets, this ſhould make him more carefull and ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous; If <hi>Abigail</hi> bee encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and releeuing thoſe that fight the battels of the Lord, this ſhould make her more cheerefull and magnificent; If the Preacher bee hewing, and ſlaſhing at ſinne, this ſhould make him more induſtrious and reſolute, conſidering that there hath not beene ſo much, as a good purpoſe in thy heart; thou haſt not once opened thy mouth in the Lords cauſe, thou haſt not gl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a droppe of water to one of his Diſciples, thou haſt not
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:5459:90"/>releeued one of his members, thou haſt not preferred one of his Prophets; thou haſt not broken the heart, nor woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the head, nor ſtaunched the paſſage of any one ſinne, but God hath ſeene it, and penned it downe, and doth remember it, and will reward it: Goe on then in the name and bleſſing of God; and if thou haue goods releeue Chriſt Ieſus in his afflicted members with it: If thou haue learning, make the Church of GOD thine adopted heire, and leaue ſome remembrance in it: If thou haue authoritie ſhew it in cutting off ſinne that endangers the Land; in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of life to Religon, which now lies in a ſwoone; ſhew it in ſcourging and whipping of vice: bring glorie to thy God
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:5459:90"/>comfort to thy ſoule, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and immortalitie to thy Countrie by it. If thus thou haue behaued thy ſelfe, then goe on and the Lord bee with thee: And as thou go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thus cheere vp thy heart. Great was the good I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, though I haue not performed it: Laboured I haue, though not much preuailed; I haue coped with ſinne, though I could not diſcomfite it; I haue ſnaped the growth of ſome vngodlineſſe, though I could not digge vp the rootes of it: I haue done my beſt, though that which is beſt I haue not done. Shall I bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged becauſe I can but doe my beſt, and not ſo much as I ſhould? Surely no. I will ſtill bee doing ſome good, and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to doe better; if I mend
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:5459:91"/>and doe neuer ſo much; I will ſtriue to doe more; If I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, God ſhall haue glorie, if I preuaile not, yet ſtill I will ſtriue; becauſe there is nothing that I doe or purpoſe, but my God doth ſee it, writes it in his booke, doth remember it, and will reward it.</p>
                  <p>Thus hee that doth good hath had his encouragement. <hi>The next</hi> is hee that endureth afflictions: If I may beg your attention till I haue reached him but a morſell of comfort, I will preſently proceede to that which followes. Giue mee a man hath not liued ſo many minutes of time, as hee hath reade and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed whole decads and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of woe; or a man that hath not eaten ſo many mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of bread, as hee hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:5459:91"/>whole loades and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens of griefe, or a man that neuer taſted ſo many droppes of drinke, as hee hath ſhedde ſtreames and riuers of teares; or a man that hath no follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er but paine, no retainer but diſcontent, no companion but griefe of heart; that pennes no ſongs but ſad complaints, and mournefull Elegies; that endites no deſcants but ſighes and groanes, that ſings no tunes but <hi>Lachrimae;</hi> giue mee ſuch a man as this, and you ſhall ſee, that this little ſprigge of balme, which I pluckt from my Text, will make him whole and ſonnd againe: And this is it. <hi>The Lord ſees thee.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">An encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to endure affliction.</note> Thou doſt not ſhed a teare for his ſake, but hee puts it into his bottle, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56. <hi>ver.</hi> 8. The enemy hath not made a ſcarre or a ſcratch in
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:5459:92"/>thy face, but hee accounts it done vnto himſelfe; Thou haſt not ſweat one droppe of water for his ſake, but hee that ſweat droppes of bloud for thee, hee doth regard it. There is not one furrow in thy backe, but hee both ſearcheth the wound, and prouideth balme and oyle to ſupple it.</p>
                  <p>This was it that comforted <hi>Elias</hi> in the Wilderneſſe, and <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Caue; and <hi>Iob</hi> on the dunghill, and <hi>Ieremie</hi> in the dungeon; and this is it that muſt cheere and comfort thee; euerie ſigh that thou fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt, euerie teare thou ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, euery drop thou ſweateſt, euery wound thou feeleſt, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtroke thou beareſt, euerie threat thou endureſt, is both ſeene and noted, and recorded, in Gods Writing-booke, and
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:5459:92"/>when that Booke ſhall be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, then ſhall all teares be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from thine eyes, then ſhall thy wounds bee waſhed with oyle, then ſhall thy ſores bee healed with balme, <hi>Et haec olim meminiſſe iuuabit,</hi> Thou ſhalt remember with ioy the dayes and nights which thou haſt paſſed in heauineſſe, then no more ſowing in teares, but reaping in ioy: Then no more mournefull Elegies, but this, or ſome higher ſtrayne of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly eloquence: I was wont to bee brewing and ſpending of teares, but now am I ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and bathing in pleaſure: For euerie teare doe I finde ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of Comfort, for euerie moment of griefe, a world of contentment, I had once no Songs, but ſighs and ſobbes, no tunes, but groanes: But now
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:5459:93"/>my ſighes are turned, and my grones are changed into Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luiahs, my dittie is Halleluiah, my ſtraines Halleluiah, Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luiah. Glorie, and praiſe, and honour be aſcribed, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Thus this one poynt, that God deſcrieth our workes, and purpoſes, ingeminates &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes a woe and terror to the hypocrite, and the Adulterer, but encouragement to the good, and to the afflicted ſtore of comfort, I cloſe it thus. God ſees thee Hypocrite, heereafter diſſmble not. God ſees thee Adulterer, heereafter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it not agayne. God ſeeth thee good Chriſtian, goe on and feare not, God ſeeth thee afflicted ſoule, goe on and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire not. Hypocrite God ſees thee, then be as good as thou wouldeſt bee accounted, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:5459:93"/>God ſeeth thee, then doe not that on the night, which on the day light thou dareſt not. Good Chriſtian, GOD ſeeth the, continue in doing well, hee will ſhortly crovvne thee. Afflicted man, God ſees thee, ſtand and ſweate, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, hee is now comming to releaſe thee. And ſo I proceed from Gods excellent preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue: <hi>I know thy wayes,</hi> To the crime obiected againſt <hi>Laodicea; Thou art neyther hote nor cold.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Not to trouble you vvith ſuch a varietie of expoſitions, as <hi>Pererius</hi> out of <hi>Haimo,</hi> out of <hi>Gregorie</hi> in the third of his <hi>Paſtoralles,</hi> as alſo out of <hi>Lira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and <hi>Bernard,</hi> and <hi>Ruper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> haue noted readie to my hand. Out of the verie beſt of them, I thinke I may thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue. By <hi>Hote,</hi> I meane a man
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:5459:94"/>zealous of Gods honour, and worſhippe, whoſe zeale is built and founded on knowledge, whoſe heart is not infected, nor taynted with pride. By <hi>Colde,</hi> I meane ſuch chill and frozen caitiffes, as doe wedde and eſpouſe themſelues vnto the world, and make no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of religion.<note place="margin">who are to be meant by hote, &amp; cold, and lukewarm.</note> By <hi>Lukewarm,</hi> I meane ſuch as do diuide their loue betweene GOD and the world, and their ſeruice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and <hi>Baal,</hi> and their allegeance betweene God and <hi>Mammon,</hi> that loue God in word, but the world in heart, that profeſſe Religion onely ſo farre, as religion makes for their commodity. The ſecond ſort of profeſſors, which are colde Chriſtians, the Lord will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe. The Third ſort, which are Luke-warme Goſpellers, the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:5459:94"/>Lord wil ſpue out of his mouth, onelie the firſt who haue giuen the world and <hi>Baal</hi> their bills of Diuorce, and ſent them away, and not onelie abiured them, but are zealous for the glorie and worſhip of the GOD of Heauen, theſe onely are heere commended, their ſeruice one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie is accepted. So that my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine cometh off with eaſe, and thus offers it ſelfe to meete me in the way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The profeſsion of religion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out zeale and forwardneſſe is odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and loathſome vnto God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Profeſsion without zeale is odious.</note> For euidence, I appeale to the ſiluer Trumpets of Heauen, and the Watchmen of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> reade vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, what might be the cauſe why <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the 32. chapter of <hi>Exodus</hi> ſhould wiſh to be razed out of the Booke of Life; why <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>Romanes</hi> the 9. chapter,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:5459:95"/>the third, ſhould deſire a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the protection and loue of Chriſt? was it not the fire of their zeale, and the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencie of their Spirit, that made them thus impatient of the leaſt impeachment, that could bee offered to the glory of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne and maieſtie of their God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> the Seede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Religion, their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the prop and ſtay whereon the Church of God doth leane, their liues like to that Starre in the ſecond chapter of Saint <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> to bring vs to CHRIST; and yet all their preaching, had it wanted zeale, and their profeſſion, had it wanted heate, and their ſeruice, had it wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this earneſt longing, and ardencie of affection, to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite and honour their Lord
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:5459:95"/>and Maiſter, all their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had beene but vayne, all their profeſſion but formall, all their ſeruice but ſmoothe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling in the ſight of God. If <hi>Ioſiah</hi> had onelie refuſed to bow and kneele to <hi>Baal,</hi> or had hee onelie profeſſed the ſeruice of the true God, and gone no farther, he had endured as ſharp a cenſure as <hi>Azariah</hi> the King of <hi>Iudah.</hi> Hee did vprightly in the ſight of God, but the high places were not taken avvaie, and therefore the Lord ſmote him, the ſecond Booke of the <hi>Kings,</hi> and 15. chapter. And the Scriptures would not haue ſo much commended him, but becauſe he was zealous for the glorie of GOD, becauſe hee was forvvard to deſtroy their Groues, and zealous to breake downe their Chemarims, and
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:5459:96"/>forward to throw downe their Altars, &amp; ſacrifice their prieſts, this was it that God liked, and this was it that the Scriptures commended: and this was it that wonne him high title and immortall honour from all the Kitgs that were eyther before or after him: the ſecond Booke of <hi>Kings</hi> the 23. chapter and the 25. verſe. It is not to be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned but that this <hi>Laodicea</hi> a Church ſo famous, did make profeſſion of religion, did wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the true and immortall dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, did giue eare and attention to the preaching of <hi>Iohn,</hi> was throughly acquaynted with all the grounds and principles of the Chriſtian faith. We reade of no hereſie that ſhee maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, of no ſuperſtitious worſhip that ſhe harboured, and yet he will ſpue her out of his mouth.
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:5459:96"/>The abhomination of deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt bee ſet vp in her high places. She muſt fall as though ſhee had neuer beene planted, and wither as though the ſeede of the Word had neuer beene rooted, her Churches muſt be ſackt, her ancient glorie muſt end in ſhame; In ſtead of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Bible, ſhe muſt roue at the way to Heauen in an vnhallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and blaſphemous <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and in ſtead of skilfull Pilots, and Chriſtian guides, ſhe ſhall bee vtterly miſ-led by an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> I meane Turkes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels: reade now vnto me what might be the cauſe of this. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odicea</hi> was much of <hi>Ephraims</hi> temper, in the ſeuenth of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> like a cake vpon the hearth but halfe baked, <hi>Laodicea</hi> was like the people of <hi>Meroz</hi> in the fifth of the <hi>Iudges,</hi> nothing forward.
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:5459:97"/>
                     <hi>Laodicea</hi> was like thoſe ſhrinkers in the ninth of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> that had no courage for the truth, ſhee wanted heate in her profeſſion, ſhee wanted life and ſpirite in Chriſts cauſe, ſhe moſt of all wanted that which hee moſt of all required, and that was zeale, <hi>nullum enim Deo gratius ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium, quam zelus animarum,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> in the twelfth ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily vpon <hi>Ezechtel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which poynt will one day naile the heart, and cut deep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the conſcience of all thoſe that haue ſo much to doe in the Lords cauſe, but doe either lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing for it. And ſhall I without offence make bolde to tell you that which I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from the Lord, and doe the meſſage for vvhich I came hither: Then let me firſt begin with the faireſt; It is you (right
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:5459:97"/>Honourable) into whoſe hands the Lord hath put his Sword, for no other purpoſe, but to ſtrike at the roote, and to draw at the face, and to ayme at the heart and ſtrength of ſinne; if you ſuffer your Sword to ruſt in your ſheathe, and your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes to rot in your quiuer; if you haue a faire profeſſion, and yet we finde no good you haue done; if you carry a Sword, and yet we heare tell of no ſinne you haue wounded; be a ſouldier of Chriſt to quarrell vvith ſinne, and yet wee remember no field you haue pitched; if God haue honoured you, and you not honoured him, by baiting and hazling of ſinne, by cooling the heate, and breaking the heart, &amp; taunching the violent iſſue of vngodlineſſe, Where then is your zeale? If God be diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:5459:98"/>and you not reuenge it, if vertue diſcouraged, and you not defend it; if religion be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, and our land endangered by the inroades and incurſions of ſinne, and you ſhall not help it; where then is your zeale? If Sabboths bee broken, and you haue authoritie, and yet not ſuppreſſe it; If ſwearing and drunkenneſſe be accounted but complement, and you haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and ſhall not oppoſe it. If ſinne may ſit in your ſhope and feed at your boordes, and jette in your Markets; and you haue a Sword and yet will not ſtrike it; If God ſay, ſtrike, or elſe thou diſhonoreſt mee; ſtrike or elſe I will take the ſword from thee; ſtrike, or elſe thou fighte againſt me; ſtrike, or elſe I will ſtrike at thee, &amp; yet no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but you will reprieue it
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:5459:98"/>where then is your zeale? Let me not offend, I condemne you not, <hi>Qui monet vt facias quod iam facis, ipſe monendo laudat.</hi> I am only your remembrancer to put you in minde of whetting your ſword, for a ſword with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an edge may fright, but woundeth not: to put you in minde of heating and warming your profeſſion. For profeſſion without zeale, is but like the ſnuffe of a candle, that ſmoketh and ſtinketh, but neyther war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth nor lighteth the houſe, to put you in minde of that cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage which you ſhould beare, and of that conſcience which you ſhould make of the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of ſinne, of the honouring of God, of aduauncing Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leſt the ſword which you beare, prooue a naile vnto your heart, and the honor which you
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:5459:99"/>beare a diſhonour to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; to put you in minde, that a Chriſtian profeſſion, that a high and honourable calling ſhould ſtill bee beautified and graced with zeale, and attended with chriſtian reſolution. If then you be willing to fight for your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, if willing to honour and credit your maker; if you would haue Religion thanke you, and the world to thinke well of you, good men to praiſe GOD for you, Gods people to pray for you, the heauens to bleſſe you, and all mouthes to commend you, all hearts to loue you; then muſt you adde zeale to your profeſsion, then ſtring vp your bowe, make your arrowes ſwift and keene, your ſword ſharpe and gliſtering, and I beſeech God to ſtrengthen both your heart and hand, to ſharpen both
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:5459:99"/>your Arrowes and Sword, to bleſſe you and your good ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorus, that you may bring much honorto his dreadful name, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bleſsings to this famous Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, much peace and comfort to your ſoules.</p>
                  <p>And ſeeing I am thus farre proceeded, let me haue leaue to adde a word or two, to the wiſe and reuerend Iudges of the Land; you are they whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion it is to free the weake &amp; impotent, from the yoke and ſeruitude of greater perſonages, who would ſwallow them vp, to loppe and prune the corrupt and rotten branches, that infect and peſter the Land, to cut off the trayterous heads of Prieſts and Ieſuites, that hinder the peace, to whip and cenſure our beſotted Recuſants, that repine at the growth of the Goſpell,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:5459:100"/>yet if this godly profeſſion want zeale in performing, if our laws be ſoueraigne but want executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if you be good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but want reſolution, if the poor client ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licite that his cauſe may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if the country beſeech that offenders may bee puniſhed, if the Preachers entreate and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, for the glory of God, for the honour of our Land, for the peace of our Church, for the ſafetie of his Maieſties roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all perſon, that you would wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the forces, and abate the pride, and fruſtrate the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and eyther baniſh or binde to allegiance our hollow-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and popiſh fondlings, and you ſhall not heare the ſuites, nor ſatisfie the hopes of our Church and State that crie and call for the ſweeping and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of our land of all noyſome
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:5459:100"/>and infeſtious weedes, which the enuious man of Rome hath ſowen and planted; then you doe more diſhonour God by want of zeale, then euer you can honour him by your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: If therefore you deſire to make your profeſſion glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, your graces eminent; if you deſire to make Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to you, good men to bleſſe God for you, our Land to thanke and reward you, the Church to pray for you, all hearts to loue you, all mouthes to commend you, and Gods bleſſing vpon you, then muſt you adde zeale to profeſſion. Bee zealous like <hi>Iehu,</hi> for the glory of God, 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 10. Bee zealous to breake the threed of contentions without demurres and delaies: Bee zealous to eaſe the Church of thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:5459:101"/>and wraſtle in her wombe, to eaſe the Land from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> from the one end to the other, of all ſuch ſpitefull miſcreants as deſire and long to ſee the Scepter remoued from <hi>Iuda:</hi> that ſpeake of vs as <hi>Scipio</hi> in <hi>Polibius</hi> did of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Polibius apu Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> at the burning of <hi>Carthage, Illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies veniet, cum flamma hac tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla peribunt;</hi> who haue hope that they ſhall one day ſee our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches burned, our Cities ſackt, our courage daunted, our State ſubuerted, our Religion altered, our Soueraigne buried, the Goſpell ſilenced, and our light remoued: But ô thou wiſe and immortall God, that ſitteſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the circle of the heauen, and ſeeſt what theſe bloud-ſucking and deplored wights are deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againſt Thee, and thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed Seruant; againſt thy
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:5459:101"/>poore Church and true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, againſt our State &amp; againſt our Kingdome; fill the hearts of our Magiſtrates with zeale, ſtrengthen their hands with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and courage to cut them off: infatuate the counſell of theſe <hi>Achitophels,</hi> but grant ioyand peace vnto thy Church, long life and happineſſe to our gratious Soueraigne, puritie and continuance of true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, growth and paſſage to the Goſpell, glory and immortall happineſſe to this State and Kingdome. Lord ſay Amen to our requeſts, and let euery one that loues this Nation, that cares for <hi>Syon,</hi> that fauours Religion, that wiſheth well to our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, helpe mee with their prayers, hold vp their hands, and lift vp their voyces to heauen and ſay, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="192" facs="tcp:5459:102"/>
                  <p> And ſeeing I am thus farre proceeded, deny mee not your attention till I haue left a word of exhortation to my brethren of the Cleargy; You are they whoſe breaſts ſhould bee ſigned with <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> and your fore-heads marked with this inſcription, <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord, Exod.</hi> 28.36. your profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the winning of ſoules, your charge weighty; if you win them great is your glory, if you looſe them your danger intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. But if your people lie at the ſide of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> and you will not trouble the water for them; if they long for the crums of your ſpirituall benediction, and ſhall not obtaine them; if they would ſit at your feete to heare your Preaching; if they gaſpe for this heauenly bread, and cry for the waters of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:5459:102"/>and yet muſt ſtarue and die for want of them; then your want of care makes your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion odious; your want of zeale makes your profeſſion dangerous; your want of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe in Religion, makes Religion be termed but policie; you can neuer gaine ſo many ſoules by your profeſſion, as you may deſtroy and murther for want of zeale. <hi>Iohn</hi> was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a lampe ſhining in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, but a torch burning with zeale; <hi>Nam qui non ardet, non ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendit,</hi> ſaith S. Barnard: <hi>nec luce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re poteſt niſi priùs ardeat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquinas</hi> vpon the fifth of <hi>Iohn;</hi> If your ſelues burne not with zeale how can you enflame the hearts of others? If you burne not your ſelues, then can you giue no light to others. You are <hi>Lucernae quoad officium,</hi> but <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctae
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:5459:103"/>quoad effectum,</hi> like ſnuffes in the midſt of a golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke: Suffer mee then to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort and charge you all, that looke for ioy and comfort on the bed of your ſickneſſe, that look for a gracious welcome to the Supper of the Lambe; that wold haue your heads crowned, and your ſoules ſaued at the laſt day, that now in the prime of your life, and the light of the Goſpell, you would adde bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning zeale to Chriſtian profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for then wold good Lawes be ſtrictly executed, then wold ſinne be ſharply puniſhed, then would our Recuſants be round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſured, then would the Goſpell bee frequently Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, then would Religion flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and God be highly honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. But alas for vs all, where or in whom ſhall we find it? where
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:5459:103"/>is the glowing of the eares? where is the wringing of the hands? Where is the beating of the breaſts? Where is the ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kling of the eyes? Where is the yearning of the Bowels? The ſhaking of the fleſh? The pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the heart? The thrift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Gallants are out-vying of oathes, and our bearts are not wounded; your obſcoene and Whoriſh ſtages bereaue this Land of many hopefull ſprigs, depriue the Gentry of many hopefull ſtemmes, fill this Citie with prodigious vices; turne good, and ingenuous, and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full natures, into prodigall and diſſolute, and lewde profeſſors, and yet our hearts are not nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, where then is our zeale? God is diſhonoured, Recuſants are and will bee ſuffered, ſinne is and will be maintained, zeale
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:5459:104"/>is and muſt bee taunted; a good conſcience is &amp; muſt be laught out of countenance; Religion is and muſt bee brought vnder hatches, and ſent a begging, and yet our hearts are not moued, where then is our zeale?</p>
                  <p>And becauſe there is no point wherein a man may ſooner ouer-ſhoote himſelfe then in this, I will in a word or two deliuer ſome plaine and eaſie rules whereby a man may iudge whether his zeale be currant or counterſeit.<note place="margin">Markes of true zeale.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 The matter muſt be good <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.18.<note place="margin">The 1.</note> or elſe it is not zeale but deuilliſh and fleſhly heate a frenzie, and madneſſe, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting the name of zeale like the zeale of thoſe Idolater that mangled and cut them ſelues, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. Like the zeal of the Scribes and Phariſe
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:5459:104"/>who compaſſe Sea and Land to make Proſelites: Like the zeale of <hi>Paul</hi> before his conuerſion: Like the zeale of ignorant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Browniſts at this day, who are hot indeed; for they muſt needes runne whom the deuill driues, <hi>Sed incaleſcunt in re frigida:</hi> They are like bittes of lime neuer ſo hot and ſmoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as in cold water, neuer ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt but in euill canſes: Which may bee hence conuicted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they vſe no weapons but ſuch as the deuill puts into their hands, to wit, rayling and detracting, and rotten ſpeeches the onely Patrons for ſuch bad cauſes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Zeale muſt beginne at home;<note place="margin">The 2.</note> for they are moſt skilfull Phiſitians, and beſt able to deale with others, that haue firſt wrought a cure vpon their
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:5459:105"/>owne ſoules; to checke all thoſe that wade deep into the ſoules, and bloudily go are the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of other men, but haue not purged their own vncleane ſinkes at home; no not drawne one droppe of menſtruous bloud, out of their owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and rotten hearts: Like Phariſes who cenſured Chriſt but not themſelues; like Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, who ſtretch their veines, and make their bowels ſwell, with crying, <hi>Diſorder, Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> amongſt vs, but leaue ſinkes of ſinne vnpurged, cages of ſinne vncleanſed, bands and troupes of ſinne vntamed and vnvanquiſhed vnder their owne roofes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 True zeale will looke as carefully to the heart before God,<note place="margin">The 3.</note> as the behauiour in the ſight of men, and make a man
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:5459:105"/>as fearefull to ſinne, when hee is alone, as when hee is in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of men. Thus it wrought with <hi>Iob, chap.</hi> 31. And thus with <hi>Ioſeph, Gen.</hi> 39. A check to thoſe that would not bee accounted ill, but make no conſcience of doing ill; that would bee called good men, but haue no heart to good actions.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 If it bee true zeale it will make thee more ſtrict to thy ſelfe, then to others,<note place="margin">The 4.</note> and giue more liberty to another then thou wilt take thy ſelfe; <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was ſo ſtrict to himſelfe, that he would not take of the King of <hi>Sodome,</hi> ſo much as a threed, or ſhoe-latchet, and yet would not deny to <hi>Aner</hi> and <hi>Eſchol</hi> and <hi>Mamre,</hi> their liberty <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.23. and therefore it muſt bee termed rather pride then zeale to bee too tetricall
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:5459:106"/>and rough, that whoſoeuer is not in euery point ſo preciſe as ourſelues, ſhould bee turned out as dogs, or prophane perſons vnworthy of our account and countenance.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 True zeale feareth not the faces of the mighty;<note place="margin">The 5.</note> when we muſt beware of their preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitancy, who will charge the Miniſter to bee of a cold conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, if hee break not abrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into open reprehenſion men in authority; which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to reproue without the ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> of meekneſſe, to exaſperate ther then to humble the part admoniſhed.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">The 6.</note> if it bee true zealed wil make thee brook and po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> many priuate wrongs done thy ſelfe, but hot and impati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> of any diſhonour vnto G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> offered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="201" facs="tcp:5459:106"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uate wrongs to <hi>Moſes,</hi> hee was wont to ſpeak mildely and pray earneſtly for them; but when they fell to Idolatry, a matter which concerned God, then his fire was kindled, then hee breakes the Tables, and ſtampes the Calfe to powder, and caſts the aſhes into the water, and makes them to drinke vp their God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.</p>
                  <p>I feare I haue dwelt too long vpon the point, the cloſure is but this; Let vs all beſtirre our ſelues when Gods cauſe is a judging, and bee earneſt when his glory is in queſtion; bee zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to ſtrike when hee himſelfe puts the ſword in our hands; be calous to ſpeake when himſelfe puts the word in our mouthes: let euery one that weares the coate and liuery of Chriſt, write <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eale vpon his breaſt, And ô
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:5459:107"/>thou holy and bleſſed Spirit come vnto vs as thou cameſt to thine Apoſtles, in ſhape of fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie tongues, that our tongues may bee tipt and enamuled, our hearts ſeaſoned, our ſoules en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed, our profeſſion graced with zeale of thy honour and worſhip, that ſinne may bee ſhaken, thy Name exalted, thy Truth embraced, our Church continued, our Land bleſſed, our ſoules ſaued, when theſe few and miſerable daies ſhall be ended. And ſo I come from the crime obiected,<note place="margin">The crime obiected againſt <hi>Laodicea.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Thou art neither hot nor cold,</hi> to ſee how the ſinne is aggrauated in the next words, <hi>Would God thou wert ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hot or cold.</hi> Which words are not ſo to be vnderſtood, as if they ſhould haue pleaſed him well enough, had they bene either hot or cold, or any thing
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:5459:107"/>but luke-warme, <hi>Non oſtendit quid probat, ſed quid praefert,</hi> but his meaning was to let them know, that hee ſo diſliked luke-warmeneſſe in Religion, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differencie in profeſſion of Chriſtianitie, that he ſhould haue liked them better, and their condition ſhould not haue bin ſo deſperate, had they made no conſcience, or had no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as now it was by their hypocriſie and want of zeale: ſo that the point which by the Holy Ghoſt is heere deliuered, may bee compriſed in theſe tearmes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It were better to bee of no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion at all,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Better to bee of no Religion then to be luke-warm</note> 
                     <hi>then to diuide our loue betweene God and the world, and our ſeruice betweene God and Baal, and our attendance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and Mammon; or to embrace Religion no farther, then
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:5459:108"/>Religion ſerues our turne to gaine withall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which Theoreme howſoeuer it be the deduction of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and of the whole current both of Moderne, and Ancient In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, yet ſhall it bee no waſte of time to ſupport and fence it, by copying a place or two out of Gods Writing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booke; turne but your leafes vnto the 9. of <hi>Iohn</hi> the 41. and view our Sauiours anſwere to the Phariſes queſtion; <hi>Had you beene blind you ſhould not haue ſinned;</hi> That is, ſay <hi>Bucer,</hi> and <hi>Muſculus,</hi> and <hi>Aquinas</hi> agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the gloſſe, Your ſinne had not beene ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſinnefull as now it is; as if our Sauiour had thus enlarged his ſpeech: There is no man that hath not gone aſtray euen from the wombe; The moſt
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:5459:108"/>righteous before men is defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and ſpeckled in the ſight of God, and may go crying all the day long with the Leper, <hi>Leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus</hi> the 13. chapter and verſe 45. <hi>I am vncleane, I am vncleane:</hi> but you diſſembling Phariſees are more deepely ſtayned then anie other, your ſinnes are high coloured like crimſon, vvhich (as <hi>Lipſius</hi> obſerueth) is twice dyed; other men haue Moats,<note place="margin">Lipſius de Conſtantia. libro. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> but you haue Beames in your eyes, other men haue Scrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but you haue Wounds and Scarres in your Faces, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may ſwallow ſinnes as bigge as Gnats, but you can digeſt ſinnes as bigge as Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mells, and how is it that your ſinnes are more inexpiable then other mens? it is becauſe you ſerue mee not in ſinceritie, and profeſſe religion onely for your
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:5459:109"/>profite, and diuide your loue betvvixt mee and your ovvne <hi>Mammon,</hi> it had beene better for you, to haue worſhipped onelie <hi>Mammon,</hi> and neuer to haue heard of me, it had beene better for you to haue truſted onelie to your owne wits, and neuer to haue truſted mee, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you truſt onely mee, and better for you to haue beene ſtarke blinde, then onely to ſee how you may turne your backs, and looke a-ſquint at Heauen; it were better to haue been cold dead, then to be as it were in an Iſtmus;<note place="margin">Heinſy Poem.</note> 
                     <hi>Vt tundat mentem fluctus vterque tuam:</hi> to bide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt life and death, to haue thy Religion ebbing and flowing,<note place="margin">Plutarch. de Socratis Genio. Heſych. de vita Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophorum.</note> thy profeſſion like the ſoule of <hi>Hermotimus</hi> in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and of <hi>Epimenides</hi> in <hi>Heſychius</hi> coming and going. Let thy Religion be
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:5459:109"/>eyther pure and ſound, or none, thy profeſſion eyther entire and ſound, or none, thy zeale eyther burning hote, or none, to be blinde, to be of no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, to make no conſcience of Religion is verie damnable: but to ſee the way, and not to follow it, to profeſſe Religion, and not to be zealous for it, to weare CHRISTS Liuerie, and ſerue anie other beſides the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that gaue it, is intolerable. Adde vnto this that clauſe of the Apoſtle, cited to this very pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe by <hi>Gregorie,</hi> in the third of his Paſtoralls, out of the ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>Peter,</hi> chapter 2. and the 21. verſe. It were better ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to haue knowne the way, then after knowledge to turne out of it. Which one place, by generall conſent, is ſufficient to make good our poynt, the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:5459:110"/>(which in the Apoſtles ſtile) knows not, is like the colde man in my Text, that cares not for Religion, the backe-ſlider in the Apoſtles ſtile, that turneth aſide, is like vnto the Luke-warme Chriſtian in my Text, that careth not whether Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſinke or ſwimme, whether his profeſſion doe ſtand or fall, who like to <hi>Metius Suffetius</hi> in <hi>Liuie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Liuy</hi> in his firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cade and firſt Book.</note> will ſtrike or ſpeake for neyther ſide, vntill one ſide bee downe, and then ioyne to that which is beſt, for their commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie. A thing odious amongeſt Heathens, and therefore prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by <hi>Solon,</hi> That anie man ſhould ſtand as a neuter betwixt two,<note place="margin">Strigellius in <hi>3.</hi> Apoc</note> as <hi>Strigellius</hi> remembreth in his Commentarie vpon this place, a thing cryed downe by <hi>Elias,</hi> in the firſt booke of the <hi>Kings</hi> 18. chapter, and a courſe
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:5459:110"/>as damnable as is the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of a diuell, as <hi>Origen</hi> in his eight booke againſt <hi>Ceiſus</hi> that godleſſe heathen, and a ſinne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for a dreadfull woe gone out againſt it, <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 2. verſe 13.</p>
                  <p>The whole Catalogue of beſt Interpreters will yeelde a large ſupply of Reaſons to ſupport and fence my Propoſition.<note place="margin">Reaſon out of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories</hi> 3. Paſtor.</note> I will but poynt at one alleadged by <hi>Gregorie,</hi> thus ſpeaking to the poynt in hand. It is better to be cold then luke-warme in religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; not becauſe the luke warme ſinnes more hainouſly, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is reclaymed more hardly; <hi>Dum enim ſe ſanum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, medicinae opem non quaerit,</hi> ſay <hi>Marlorat</hi> and <hi>Ribera.</hi> He is like <hi>Harpaſtes</hi> in <hi>Seneca,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> ſuppoſing he ſeeth the true waie to Heauen, though hee be poſting to Hell,
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:5459:111"/>and will not bee turned, drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of nothing but of life and happineſſe, though he be wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in the menſtruous rags of ſins pollution, and will not be clenſed, thinking it the ſafeſt courſe, to walke onely betwixt two waies, betwixt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Baal,</hi> betwixt <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Mammon,</hi> to take God in one hand, and the world in the other, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but to purchaſe Hell by wit and policie, and yet this is the luke-warme Chriſtians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, that muſt not be alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. It was the ſaying of Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>Prou.</hi> chapter 26. There is more hope of a foole, then of him that is wiſe in his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and I match it thus; There is more hope of reclayming the fooliſh and the ignorant, that knoweth not vvhat Religion meanes, then of him that makes
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:5459:111"/>Religion like a Shepheards cur, neuer to barke but when Policie and Preferment ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund it.</p>
                  <p>By which poynt, a man may iudge of the wofull caſe and hopeleſſe condition of all ſuch indifferent and hollow profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, as vſe Religion onely for a ſtirroppe, whereby they may mount to rich preferments, and of ſuch as weare Gods liuery on their backes, but keep a lodging for <hi>Baal</hi> in their hearts, and of ſuch as ſtand equally affected to all Religions, who will crie aloude, God ſaue King IAMES, when they are with vs, and yet would kiſſe the feete of <hi>Paulus Quintus</hi> his Holineſſe, if they were in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and of all ſuch as do want that holy and godlie zeale, which ſhould be ſeated in the heart, and ſeene in the life
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:5459:112"/>of ſound Profeſſours; for all theſe are but Luke-warme, and therefore their caſe more feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, their amends more hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, their recouerie more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likelie, their ſaluation more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, then if they were the ſons and children of Heathens that neuer heard of God. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member this, ye Romiſh fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, ye part ſtakes with Chriſt in matter of ſaluation, ye exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate the vertue of his death, yee thinke the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt an vnfit coate to couer your ſhame, you will haue Fig-leaues of your owne to couer it, you thinke Chriſt too weake &amp; faint an Orator, to begge your pardon, and to purchaſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſubſtitute in his roome your owne inherent righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which ſhall commaund it, you offer the ſacrifice of prayſe
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:5459:112"/>for your ſaluation, not vnto CHRIST, but vnto your owne workes which haue deſerued it; you doe thinke the Sonne of God vnfitte to ſtand betweene God and you, but your owne liues, they are ſo holie, your ovvne vertues, they are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, your owne workes, they are ſo perfect and meritorious, that although ſinne haue locked the doores of Heauen againſt you, yet theſe can open it, be Gods iuſtice neuer ſo infinite, yet theſe can anſwer it; be his wrath neuer ſo hote, yet theſe can quench it, though Heauen be neuer ſo hard to come by, yet theſe may challenge it. A woe therefore muſt needes betide you, becauſe you are neyther hote to giue him, nor colde to deny him; neyther hote to giue him his owne, nor cold to denie
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:5459:113"/>all the glorie due vnto him, and therefore your caſe is the more fearefull, your amends more hopeleſſe, your ſaluation more deſperate, then they that haue no hope, then they that know no meanes, then they that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thinke of the way, then they that neuer talke of the ioy, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dreame of Immortalitie in the kingdome of Heauen; <hi>You ſhall be ſpued out of his mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Remember this, ye wauering Goſpellers, you that alter your Religion with Time and State, you that can make your Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ebbe and to flow like the ſtreame, and doe as the moſt do, and your profeſſion to waxe and waine like to the Moone, and ſhew your light onelie by fittes, or like inferiour ſtarres mooue onelie as ſome higher Planet ſhall carrie you, you that make
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:5459:113"/>your zeale like the <hi>Heliotropium,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plinius.</note> to open and manifeſt it ſelfe at euerie gleame of proſperitie, but at the falling of a ſtorme, can cloſe and ſhut your ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; your caſe is more feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, your condition more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored, your ſaluation more deſperate, then they that neuer knew what religion meant, then they that neuer heard the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel preached, or they that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had their Soules ſeaſoned with one ſparke of grace; <hi>For you ſhall be ſpued out of his mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Remember this yee Schollars of <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> who come vnto CHRIST by night onelie, you that ſeeme to beare good will to our Religion, but dare not ſhew it, becauſe your Rulers; I meane your Lords and Maiſters do diſlike it, you that haue gold and incenſe for CHRIST, but
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:5459:114"/>dare not offer it, your caſe is fearefull, your ſaluation almoſt deſperate, <hi>You muſt be ſpued out of his mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Remember this, yee media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors that would gladly conclude a marriage between the Church of God &amp; a Romiſh ſynagogue, and patch a religion like <hi>Sergius</hi> the monke,<note place="margin">Boaemus de Alcorano. li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note> of good and euill; you that would make an attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betweene the religion of Proteſtant &amp; Papiſt <hi>ſacra propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> that would haue our gold &amp; their droſſe to be ſtamped toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, our golden head to ſtand vpon their feet of clay, and Gods eternall truth to be yoaked with fooliſh and falſe traditions; you, O you are pure and perfect <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceans,</hi> you could be content to ſpeake, halfe in the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and half in the language of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> to plow with an Oxe
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:5459:114"/>and an Aſſe together, to patch ſome ſhreds of new cloth wouen by Romiſh ſpiders, into our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike and ancient veſture, ſurely your caſe is fearefull, your condition miſerable, your ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, either almoſt, or altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſperate; <hi>You muſt be ſpued out of his mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, you double hearts, you hollow neutralls and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizers, conſider and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this, you that haue the witte and skill to ſtand vpon the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches threſhold, and wee know not whether you will go in with vs, or out with our enemies, you deceitful Trumpeters and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, that giue ſuch vncertaine ſounds, that the hearer knowes not whether it be an alarume to encorage him to the fight, or a retreite to call him backe from purſuing the Romiſh aduerſary:
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:5459:115"/>ye that cannot be deſcried, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be with vs or againſt vs, conſider and remember this; The GOD of Heauen cannot endure you, his Spirit is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vvith you, his Church is diſeaſed yea and perplexed by you, you are like a draught of poyſon in her wombe, your caſe is fearefull, your condition verie miſerable, your ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on almoſt deſperate; <hi>You muſt be ſpued out of his mouth:</hi> And let vs all remember and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vvhen vvee conſider vvhat God is like to doe with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and inhabitants of this Land, who lie ſo ſicke, and are ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infected vvith this ſinne. It vvere better that our Gentrie were almoſt Iewes and Pagans, then to be hollow and giue Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion no encouragement. It were much better that Preachers
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:5459:115"/>ſhould ſtand like to <hi>Harpocrates</hi> that Egyptian god, vvith their fingers in their mouthes, then to ſpeake ſo faintly when <hi>Babel</hi> is in building, to ſpeake ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, when ſinne is encreaſing, to ſpeake ſo doubtfully, when Gods cauſe is in hearing, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer powerfully, but onelie when rich aduowſons, or great mens fauours are beſtowing. It were better for many of you Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, neuer to haue heard the name of CHRIST, neuer to haue knovvne what the Goſpell did meane; then to profeſſe ſo bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to vphold ſo weakely, the name whereby you hope to bee ſaued, to maintayne ſo poorely the Goſpell wherein you haue a Crowne propoſed, and a heauen promiſed, wee might promiſe vnto our ſelues a longer peace, vnto our kingdome more proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:5459:116"/>to our hearts more true comfort, to our conſciences more certaine reſt, to our ſoules more vndoubted ſafetie, if wee had neyther Goſpel preached, nor Religion profeſſed, nor Truth maintayned amongſt vs, then now many of vs can, for if wee doe preach Chriſt, it is ſo ſlackely; if wee doe defend the Truth, it is ſo ſlenderly; if wee doe profeſſe Religion, it is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently; if wee doe ſhoot at <hi>Babel,</hi> it is ſo weakely; if we doe ſtrike at ſinne, it is ſo faintly; if we doe God any ſeruice, it is ſo wearily performed, that many Engliſh Profeſſors do come far ſhort of theſe <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> and what then may wee thinke will God do with them?</p>
                  <p>The golden Conduites and learned Oracles of Iuſtice and Law (as <hi>Tully</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>de
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:5459:116"/>Oratore</hi> was pleaſed to ſtile them) may doe better to claſpe vp their mouthes, and throw downe their benches, and let Religion ſhift for it ſelfe as well as ſhe may, then to lie ſicke of an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> as <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> in <hi>Gellius</hi> in his 11. booke and 9 <hi>ch.</hi> when he was to pleade for the <hi>Mileſians,</hi> lay ſicke of a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <hi>ſquinancie,</hi> I meane to ſhrinke when they ſhold cut off corrupt members; or hold their hand when they ſhould eaſe the Land of her impoſtumes; or in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pollicy to forbeare the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſing of <hi>Romiſh</hi> brats, that trouble our Church and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger our Land, and maligne our Soueraigne,<note place="margin">Ouidui.</note> 
                     <hi>Vixque tenent lachrymas, quod nil lachrymabile cernunt,</hi> who pray for our clima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctericall yeare, and are ſicke to ſee the proſperity of our <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>
                     <pb n="222" facs="tcp:5459:117"/>and better for vs all, that our mothers belly had beene our Tombe; or like <hi>Ariſtotles Ephemeron</hi> in his fifth booke <hi>de hiſtoria animalium,</hi> we had peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the day that we were born; like <hi>Micaiah,</hi> 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 22. wee had taken a ſurfet of the bread and water of affliction; and better to feed with <hi>Phalaris</hi> his bull; to lye in <hi>Procruſtes</hi> his bed; or ſit with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in the ſtocks, till the ſoule giue ouer houſe-keeping in his dampie lodging, then to houer like the yong man in <hi>Zenophon</hi> betweene two waies and go on in neither;<note place="margin">Zenophon Cyrus.</note> or ſtand like an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, betweene two Religions, and ſticke neither to the one, nor to the other; or to play the hollow neutrals, and turne our backes vpon all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſaue onely when we grope a profite in it, or onely when
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:5459:117"/>we are the richer for it, or onely when wee can win a great mans fauour, or procure to our ſelues ſome honour, or preuent ſome ſhame and cenſure by it, for then wee proue our ſelues to be perfect <hi>Laodiceans, and the Lord will ſpue vs out of his mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Were I like <hi>Apollos,</hi> eloquent and powerful in the Scriptures, were my ſides braſſe, and my penne iron, and my tongue a ſiluer Trumpet, I would heere endite a Rhetoricall and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate exhortation, vnto a ſort of men, <hi>quos video volitare in fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quos ſtare ad curiam, quos eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am venere in ſenatum, ſola fundi noſtri calamitas,</hi> the onely ſcabs, and vlcers both of Church and State, as the Orator ſpeakes in his ſecond Oration againſt <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiline,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In Cat. Orat. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> I meane our Church Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:5459:118"/>who will ſerue both God and <hi>Rimmon,</hi> and our <hi>nullifidian</hi> Proteſtant, that can ſerue both God and Mammon: ô that they were wiſe, then would not the one come this day to Church with vs, and the next day to a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Synagogue to heare a Maſſe; nor the other need driuing into the Temple, like that Aſſe mentioned by <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din,</hi> in the 2. of his <hi>Demonologie,</hi> out of <hi>Lucian</hi> and <hi>Apuleius,</hi> but run from Church, like <hi>Timon</hi> in the <hi>Poet,</hi> ringing as hee goes, <hi>At mihi plaudo ipſe domi,</hi> I had rather ſee one of theſe Angels, then heare three of yonder Preachers: ô that they were wiſe, then would the one cleaue wholly either to God or <hi>Rim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and the other bow onely either to God or Mammon; then would the one either
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:5459:118"/>bring his heart with him, or giue vs his roome; and the other would come either with ſome zeale, or ſpare his labour in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a formall profeſſion: Then would they either giue God all, or take all from him; vnleſſe they will ſerue God with one halfe, and an Idoll with the other; meaning that GOD ſhould haue onely the one halfe, and an Idoll ſhould haue the other: And they meant one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to trouble God ſo farre as to ſaue the body, but let the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and the Pope agree be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues which of them two ſhould haue the ſoule. O Lord open their eyes, ô Lord turne their hearts, ô Lord pardon their ſinnes, leaſt they come into condemnation, and be ſpued out of thy mouth, which is the ſentence of male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:5459:119"/>paſſed vpon all luke-warme profeſſors, whereof in the laſt place I am to ſpeake. <hi>I will ſpue thee out of my mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which words containe an allegorie drawne from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of warme water,<note place="margin">The ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of maledicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Illyr. Bulling. &amp; Perer.</hi>
                     </note> as <hi>Illyricus</hi> and <hi>Bullinger;</hi> or from meats, as <hi>Pererius</hi> and <hi>Ribera,</hi> which if they be hot or cold, the ſtomach may retaine, but if luke-warme, it caſts them vp againe, <hi>vt ventri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus benè coquat, conſtringi debet &amp; claudi:</hi> The ſtomacke digeſts thoſe meates beſt, whereby it is ſtraitned and contracted; ſo do meates that be hot, <hi>exciecan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> contract the ſtomacke by drying, and meates that bee cold <hi>exaſperando,</hi> by wringing and pinching it; but meates that be luke-warme doe enlarge and dilate the ſtomacke; So that when nature would turne
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:5459:119"/>off any part which is hurtfull, it eaſily caſts vp all; and heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee muſt vnderſtand in the Generall, Gods infinite hatred againſt luke-warme profeſſors, and their Tragicall end: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many particulars which might bee gathered from the phraſe, <hi>I will ſpue thee out of my mouth,</hi> I haue pitcht my medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on theſe two.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 That which prouokes a man to vomite is grieuous and troubleſome, while it reſts vpon the ſtomacke, and beares the concluſion thus:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Luke-warme profeſſor is a ſore diſeaſer, and a continuall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturber of the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 That the party prouoked to vomite, is well pleaſed when the ſtomacke is well purged of the loade that troubles it; And beares the concluſion thus.</p>
                  <pb n="228" facs="tcp:5459:120"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>God is highly pleaſed, when the Church is eaſed and purged of neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trall, and hollow profeſſors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will draw a little bloud at theſe two veines,<note place="margin">The luke-warm pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour is a ſore diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church.</note> and ſet them as the vtmoſt borders and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of my diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>To beginne with the former; me thinkes the Luke-warme profeſſor may fitly bee compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with <hi>Dan,</hi> one of the ſonnes of <hi>Iacob,</hi> whom his owne father termed, <hi>an Adder that biteth the horſes and maketh the Rider to fall backward, Gen.</hi> 49. Or to a ſnuffe in the midſt of a golden Candleſticke, that cannot grace the houſe ſo much by his glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering light, as it offends the company by a loathſome and vngratefull ſmell: or to a cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſome <hi>Ephialtes,</hi> that will not ſuffer the ſpouſe to ſleepe, but proues moſt troubleſome and
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:5459:120"/>dangerous, when ſhee ſhould reſt and is leaſt ſuſpicious, or to an vnnaturall, or rather a natural viper, that firſt feeds on the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that breedes it, and then breakes the wombe that beares it. If flinching <hi>Ionas</hi> bee in the ſhip, the waters will preſently begin to boile and ſwell.<note place="margin">Virgilius Aenid. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pient ſubito nubes coelum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> diem<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> there will ſuddenly follow as thicke a <hi>Chimmerian</hi> darkenes, as there was at <hi>Pauls</hi> voyage to <hi>Rome, when neither Sunne nor Starre appeared, Act.</hi> the 27. The limbs and ioynts of the ſhippe cannot chuſe but menace and threaten preſent drowning, it can neither ſtand ſtill at An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, nor go on in ſafety; if it ſtand the waues runne ouer it; if it faile and moue, the winde and weather ouer-turnes it, there can bee neither token of
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:5459:121"/>faire weather, nor hope of life till <hi>Ionas</hi> be caſt out of it. And may it not well enough lie hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie at the heart of a tender mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (I meane the Church) that ſhee knowes not whether ſome of her ſonnes will take her part, or fight againſt her; That ſhee knowes not whether they that lie in her wombe will proue like <hi>Barnabas</hi> ſonnes of conſolation, or like <hi>Benoni,</hi> a heauineſſe and woe vnto her: How ſhould it chuſe but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex and naile her ſoule, that they whom ſhee feedeth with the milke of her breſts; that they whom ſhee honoureth with the beſt of her ſubſtance; that they whom ſhee crowneth with the richeſt of her gifts, yet for all this do not loue her? What is there that can more diſquiet &amp; diſturbe the Churches peace;
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:5459:121"/>that will ſooner make her looke old and gray; that can make deeper furrowes in her face, and plow vpon her backe with a ſharper edge then this? that ſo many of her children ſhould be ſtill-borne and cannot; ſome tongue tied and will not; ſome baſhfull and dare not ſpeake a word for Religion? that ſome of her pillars doe nothing but pill her treaſures; that ſome which ſhould doe her good, care for nothing but her goods; that ſome of her Prophets ſeeke for nothing but to profite them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? What is there that can diſquiet a Church ſo much as this, that the maior part of all Congregations ſhould be luke warme and hollow profeſſors? ſome well-willers to <hi>Dagon;</hi> ſome worſhippers of a wedge of gold; ſome making Religion
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:5459:122"/>but a ſtalking horſe, or ſome handſome drudge to ſerue their policie. This, this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but bee a naile at her heart.</p>
                  <p>Which concluſion may ſerue to ſtop the ſtentorious mouths, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> and to pare the Satyricall and bloudy pencils of ſome men, who in all their learning can ſinde none that either diſquiets or endangers the Church but the ſtrict Preciſion, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſwallow downe ſome of our Church Ceremonies, and therefore employ their whole ſtrenght, and ſpend their whole life, in humbling them who are brought already to the loweſt <hi>Nadir,</hi> as if then they had ſwept and purged the Church of all her impoſthumes; whereas yet our Churches hang full of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> ſpiders, who in their <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi>
                     <pb n="233" facs="tcp:5459:122"/>cobwebs would ſtrangle our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſoules; God forbid that euer my penne ſhould pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize any peeuiſh Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, onely it were to be wiſht, that ſome men would not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in place their felicity, or count this the greateſt ſeruice to God and the Church, to trounce and firret a few poore and deſpiſed men; but rather they would raiſe hue and cry after Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme profeſſors, and carnall Goſpellers, and cloſe Atheiſts, and ſleepy <hi>Sibarites,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Athaenaeus lib. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> that they would keepe <hi>Romiſh</hi> fire from our <hi>Engliſh</hi> tinder; theſe, theſe, are the traiterous <hi>Sinons</hi> that trouble our Church, theſe are the wormes that breed in the belly, and theſe the impoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humes that diſeaſe the wombe of our mother; ſuch hot fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zies, as Nouahaniſme, Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme,
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:5459:123"/>and Browniſme, are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or neuer heard of in this frozen climate, and the iron age wherein we liue: the moſt of our diſeaſes are cold Epilep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and dead Apoplexies, and ſlumbering lethargies, and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy ſhould bee the penne that might but wound one of the diſturbers, and happy ſhould bee the tongue that might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfite one of theſe pioners, and happy might bee the man, that might exile but one of theſe vndermining traitors out of the Church. Theſe are the ſins that threaten our ruin, and theſe the hatchets, that cut downe our Vine, and theſe the Foxes that eate of her grapes, and theſe the bels that are moſt like to ring our knels, and proclaim our funerals; and therefore euery Scribe that can handle a
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:5459:123"/>pen, muſt ſteepe it in vinegar and make it tart; euery Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that can handle a ſword muſt draw it and make it ſharp; euery man that weares but a Chriſtian heart in his boſome moſt rouſe and waken; He that hath but a tongue in his head muſt moue and ſhake it; hee that hath but a ſtone in his hand muſt throw and fling it, at the braſen faces and whoriſh fore-heads of theſe murthering and prodigious ſinnes; elſe may wee feare that one day wee ſhall feele Gods hand vpon vs and ſee deſtruction looking in at our gates, and deſolation looking in at our windowes, and finde nothing but emptineſſe in our Churches, ſee nothing but Romiſh ſpiders weauing their cobwebs in our Pulpits, <hi>Sed tarda ſit illa dies, &amp; noſtro ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:5459:124"/>aeuo,</hi> let the Sunne of that morning neuer riſe, burie vs quicke ô earth, Lord take away our liues rather then the light of our Goſpell from vs. And now haue I brought you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the view and ſight of our iournies end, I hope it will make you cheerefull in hearing, while I am briefly opening my laſt concluſion, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God is highly pleaſed,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">God high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Church of luke warm Profeſſors.</note> 
                     <hi>when his Church is eaſed and emptied of hollow profeſſors.</hi> Let them take <hi>Ionas</hi> and caſt him into the ſea; <hi>Et facto citius tumida aequora pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant,</hi> the windes will hold their peace and bee ſtill, the waues will giue ouer boyling, and make their creſts as flatte and leueli as a floore, and the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the ſhippe muſt needs haue ioyfull hearts, to ſee how merily ſhe cuts the waters, ſo
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:5459:124"/>ſoone as ſhee hath pickt vp her troubleſome loade, and empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her wombe of <hi>Ionas:</hi> whom ſhee was not able to digeſt. I know that amongſt the wheate there will be chaffe, yet if the chaffe were burned; I know that amongſt the beds of Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, there will be weedes, yet if the weedes were rooted vp; I know that within the pales and hedges of Gods owne vineyard there will be ſtones, yet if the ſtones were gathered out; the burning of the chaffe would rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh like a burnt Sacrifice, the rooting vp of the weeds would ſauour as the ſmell of Incenſe, the ridding of the ſtones would be as welcome as a free will of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering vnto God: Did not the Starres and the Heauens ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaude <hi>Elias</hi> in the firſt booke of <hi>Kings</hi> chapter 13. for reclaiming
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:5459:125"/>them that <hi>halted betweene two opinions:</hi> for ſetling them that were like to fall downe between two profeſſions, or was it not a labour well beſtowed, whereby hee cured the Land that vvas ſicke and wearie, not able to beare them, and purged their Soules that were ſicke and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to die within them, and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed his GOD, who was ſo deepely offended with them. The griefe of the head can no way be better cured, then by purging the ſtomach, and ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the bodie of ſuch infeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humours as fume vpward, and diſquiet the braine, and if Chriſt bee our head, and the Church his bodie, how ſhould you imagine that his ſpirite can be better pleaſed, or our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour delighted with any thing ſo much, as vvith the
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:5459:125"/>ſweeping out of Luke-warme profeſſors, and the paring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of aequiuocall members with the healing, if they bee cureable, or elſe the cutting off, if they be hopeleſſe and incure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able neutralls.</p>
                  <p>Were it not that the time were now ready to impoſe mee ſilence, and commaunded mee to let you ſee the fartheſt peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od, I could verie hardly part ſo quickely with ſo good a point: I winde vp all in one word of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation. I ſhould thinke my breath and trauell happily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, my Miniſterie and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice richly bleſſed, my paynes and labour highly honoured and revvarded, if I might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with authority, to prouide ſom ſtrong purgation to ſcoure out of the ſicke bodie of this Land, ſome vnwholeſome Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:5459:126"/>who <hi>Ianus</hi>-like haue two faces,<note place="margin">Ouid. Faſt. libr. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> the one to looke demure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vp to heauen, the other wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly to ſmile vpon an Idol, and come to our Churches, only to ſaue charges. If I might preuail vvith the Clergie, to prouide ſome powerfull and paſſionate exhortations to ſettle the hearts of their hearers vpon one God, renouncing Idols, vpon one Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, abiuring this ſinfull traſh and deceitfull riches. The world knoweth it full well, that our Land was neuer ſo ſick, that our Church neuer groaned ſo loud, neuer mourned in ſuch a paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor neuer trauelled of theſe Hermaphrodites, with halfe ſo much paine and griefe as novv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he doth, ſhe hath already bred, and at this day ſhee both fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and clothes a numberleſſe ſwarme of our-caſt profeſſors, I
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:5459:126"/>meane Church papiſts, and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Proteſtants, who ſometimes like vnto <hi>Iudas,</hi> pretend to kiſſe, but if they can come neere e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, intend to kill her, and ſometimes ſalute her Porches, but it is as <hi>Ioab</hi> ſaluted <hi>Abner,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Sam. 3.</note> with a dagger in their pockets, ſhe may conclude a peace with other enemies, but theſe will cut her throat by way of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſhe ſighes ſo deepely, and ſhee groaneth with ſo much an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, that her cries are heard, &amp; her griefe lamented beyond the Seas. It is no whiſpering ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, your ſelues haue often heard it cried here at the croſſe, that they are warmely lodged, and richly friended, and coſtly fed, with the marrow and fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our owne Land, who the middeſt of our Iubilies, doe make flawes in our peace, and
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:5459:127"/>in the middeſt of our ioyes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunger our liues, and if anie forrener ſhold inuade the land, wold le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their kniues to cut our throates, and be the formoſt men to beare armes againſt vs.</p>
                  <p>This alas, this is the maladie that maketh the viſage of our Church ſo wan, and her face ſo full of wrinckles, and her backe ſo ful of furrows, and her eies ſo ful of teares, and her heart ſo ful of ſorrowes, that though many good Phiſitians will ſpeake her faire, and wiſh her health, yet they lance not the Impoſtume, yet they purge not the fretting humor that conſumes and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth her, you may reade in her face, that her gripings and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be inſufferable, you may heare by her groanes, that her paine is intolerable, you may preſage by her pulſes, the ſignes
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:5459:127"/>and ſymptomes of deſolation and death, and vvhen theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike vipers haue broken her heart, what will become of vs, who ſuffer ſuch Profeſſours as will neuer prooue good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to varniſh their neaſts, and make their bowers within her: it would doe them good to do vs hurt: it would lengthen their liues, to ſhorten ours; it would bring them halfe way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to burie their ponyards in our breaſts; it would make a new Feaſt, and another Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in the Roman Kalender, if they might but ſmell the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and heare tell of the ſmoke and aſhes of our Churches, they are alreadie become ſo bolde, their number is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great, their Religion is ſo exceeding bloodie, their malice ſo inueterate, that if no
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:5459:128"/>ſharper courſe be taken to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and ſmother them, they will aduenture within a while, to try whether wee or they ſhall be the maſters; and if either ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice or multitude can do it, they wil make bone-fires of our fleſh, they will cut off our liues, and confiſcate our liuings, and ſet fire on our Churches, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre our Cleargie, and maſſacre our Iudges, and murther our Princes, and ſay of <hi>England</hi> as <hi>Edom</hi> ſayd of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> Downe with it, downe with it euen to the ground. And if euer this day of mourning come vpon vs (which I pray God may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come;) yet if it ſhould come wee may thanke our ſelues for keeping Romiſh Waſps in our Engliſh Hiues.</p>
                  <p>It were happy for our Land, if we now at laſt began to pittie
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:5459:128"/>and bemone our ſelues, and be ſomevvhat ſharpe in keeping them vnder, while we haue the ſword in our hands, rather then to ſuffer them to grow ſo long, vntill they be able to treade vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Religion, or to vaunt or triumph ouer vs. And if any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs can prepare an offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of peace, now or neuer let him bring it; hee that can vtter or conceiue a prayer, now or neuer let him offer it: Let vs moue the Heauen with crying: ſpare thy people, O God, ſpare thy people, giue not our church into reproach; Let not the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian hoſte be our maſters; Let not the blaſted Catholikes be our commaunders; Let not the workemen of <hi>Babel</hi> be our confounders.</p>
                  <p>Wil you haue your farewell and heare what Ile ſay at your
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:5459:129"/>parting? Let mee exhort you (reuerend Iudges) who walke heere in Scarlet robes, and ſit on ſeates of Iuſtice, to be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the truth, to pitty and compaſſionate our Church, to ſettle your ovvne hearts to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvare of Luke-vvarmeneſſe in your religion, that when you ſhall leaue theſe Benches, and put off theſe robes, you may ſit on Thrones amongſt the foure and twenty Elders, and be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the long white Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Saints, and follow the Lambe whereſoeuer he goeth. Let me exhort you, godlie and religious Citizens, to bee zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the truth, to vphold &amp; maintayne the Goſpel, to take heed of courſing and wandring amongſt religions, to take heed of luke-warmneſſe in your chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſion, that when you
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:5459:129"/>ſhall be put out of theſe houſes, you may be receiued into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting habitations; when you ſhall leaue your trading in this Citie, you may bee fellow-Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens with the Saints in glory, when theſe rotten poſts and worme-eaten timber of your bodies ſhall be broken downe, your ſoules may bee carried on Angels wings into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, and you alſo may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Lambe whereſoeuer hee goes. And let vs all begin this day to make our eyes ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and our heads ſprings, and our hearts fountaines of teares. And let this riuer neuer giue ouer running, let this ſpring neuer giue ouer ſwelling, let this fountaine neuer giue ouer flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; vntill this riuer of teares become a ſea, and this ſpring of teares become a floud, and this
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:5459:130"/>fountaine of teares become an Ocean, to waſh our beds, to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our couches, to make our chamber ſwimme; for the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that wee are like to bring vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelues, for the deſolation and woe which wee are like to bring vpon our Churches; for the ſolemne deſtruction, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſubuerſion which wee haue laboured to bring vpon our whole land, and vpon our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by palpable luke-warme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in our Religion, and by our want of godly zealein our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſion. And when this riuer of teares ſhall bee dried, and theſe fountaines ſtopt that wee cannot weepe. Let vs fill the aire and beate the heauens with our prayers, and though ſicknes may put our tongues to ſilence that we cannot ſpeake, yet let our hearts breath, &amp; our ſoules
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:5459:130"/>enforce vpon the heauens ſome earneſt and powerfull ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that the dreadfull God whom wee haue offended may be pleaſed to bleſſe our Church, to proſper our Soueraigne, to protect our Kingdome, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the Goſpell, to encreaſe our zeale, to cloath ourenemies in mourning weeds, to open the windowes of Heauen &amp; crowne vs with his bleſſings, to cure all our ſoules, to forgiue all our ſins, to ſaue all our ſoules, for his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus his ſake: <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
